Based on a true story.
改編自真實的故事
1953年
埃德蒙.希拉堜M丹增·諾爾蓋成為首次成功登頂珠峰的登山者。
在接下來的近40年的時間堙A只有專業的登山者才能嘗試同樣的壯舉。
其中四分之一的登山者去世。
1992年 新西蘭人，羅布·霍爾首創立業餘珠峰登山指導團的商業概念。
在接下來四年中，他的探險顧問團隊成功的帶領19名客戶登上峰頂。
沒有任何人死亡。
1996年包括斯科特·菲捨爾的瘋狂登山者在內的其他的商業團隊追隨著羅布·霍爾的腳步
超過20個探險隊在相同的兩周窗口期內競相攀登珠峰。
Please listen up.
請注意
Guys.
各位
We got 2000 feet (ft),
我們還有2000英尺
600 vertical metres (m)
垂直高度600米的距離
to Camp 4.
才到達4號營地
Let's rope all the way,
來讓我們扣緊攀登繩索
so I know you can make it.
來吧！我知道你可以到達4號營地的。
Alright, once we get to the Yellow band, we're going to regroup.
一旦我們到達黃色標記，我們將重整隊伍。
Put on the mask,turn on the gas.
戴上你的口罩，打開氧氣瓶。
Make sense?
還有其他問題嗎？
$325 a bottle,
325美元一瓶，
- for oxygen.
(6 weeks ago...)
-  氧氣
（6周前···）
- It's daylight robbery.
(6 weeks ago...)
- 這不是光天化日之下的搶劫嘛。
（6周前···）
Yeah. Well, he's cornered the market, he's got it
是啊。他不是想壟斷了這個市場嘛，他現在真的壟斷了。
He reckon there's going to be 20 teams at Base camp this season.
他估計這個登山季將會有20支隊伍到大本營。
20 teams?
20 支隊伍？
I mean with all the Sherpas and porters
我是說包括上所有的夏爾巴人和搬運工們。
it's going to be squeeze up there.
那不就會很擠嘛。
Lets...scrum on the ropes right there.
來···把混亂的繩子放在這堙C
What is this?
這是什麼？
It's Helen's.
這是海倫的東西。
It's a little decoration for the mess in.
這是這些雜亂品中的小飾品。
- Hey, you can wear them on your head, y'hear.
- I'll have it, thank you.
- 嘿，你可以把它們戴在你的頭上。
- 我會的，謝謝
Okay, I got some news.
好的，我這埵釣ヴ灡均C
- We got Krakauer.
- Huh?
- 克拉考爾將加入我們的團隊
- 恩？
Oh, yeah!
噢，好的！
- You stole him from Scott Fischer.
- No, he made his own mind.
- 你從菲捨爾斯科特那把他挖過來了？
- 沒有，他自己決定要過來的。
Good job, Rob.
幹得漂亮，羅布。
How much is he paying you, Rob?
羅布，他給了你多少錢？
Well, he's...only paying for his airfare.
好吧，他只是付了他的機票錢。
but we got 5000 words
但是我們將得到5000字的文稿
in the magazine and our picture in the front cover.  Huh.
在雜誌上和用我們的圖片作為封面。呵呵。
That makes it all worthwhile.
Right there.
這還是比較值的。
這堙C
Or if you get him to the top.
那也得你先得把他帶上頂峰吧。
If... If...How can you say that to me?
這····你怎麼可以這樣說我呢？
- There you go.
- I got you.
- 好吧
- 你懂的。
You alright? Thanks, Guy.
Cheers, mate.
你還好嗎？謝謝，夥計。
乾杯，夥計們。
- Hey.
- Hi, Rob.
- 嘿
- 你好，羅布
- Good to see you.
- Oh, yeah. How are you?
- 見到你很高興。
- 噢，是的。還好嗎？
- I am good. Oh, look at you.
- I know.
- 我很好。噢，看到你真好。
- 我知道。
- Big.
- Here you go.
- 大肚子。
- 寶貝你來了。
You good?
你還行嗎？
- Yeh, you know.
- Okay.
- 恩，你懂的。
- 好吧。
Just going to miss you.
我會想你的。
Let's go, Guy.
出發吧夥計們。
Just-Just go careful, alright?
一定··一定要注意安全，好嗎？
- It's just...
- Please don't.
- 我想說····
- 請別說什麼了。
Come on, please don't worry.
來吧，請別擔心。
It's just that doing nothing back here
that's making me worry.
在這塈琱偵繷ㄟ竣ㄓF這讓我感到很憂慮。
- You're not doing nothing.
- No, but...
- 你不是什麼都不能做。
- 好吧，可是····
What?
什麼？
It's the waiting for you.
你要為了我和孩子們一定要安全回來。
- For him.
- Ha ha.
- 為了他。
- 哈哈。
- Her.
- 為了她。
- 為了她
Just, be back for the birth,
Rob Hall.
一定，一定要回來一起迎接他的出生
羅布·霍爾。
You try and stop me.
我知道你非常不希望我去。
- Okay, I love you.
- Go, or I'll cry.
- 好吧，我愛你。
- 去吧，否者我會感動得流淚的。
Go.
走。
KATHMANDU, NEPAL
尼泊爾 加德滿都
March 30th 1996
1996年3月30日
Here.
這堙C
- That all you got.
- Yeah. That's it.
- 這就是你的全部東西？
- 是的，就這些。
I think we're over here.
我覺得我們將會在這塈像J的。
Hey...
What work outfit you guys with?
嘿···你們是和哪一個團隊一起的？
- Adventure Consultants.
- Uh, good, me too.
- 探險顧問。
- 恩，好吧，我也是。
I'm Beck.
Beck Weathers.
我是貝克。
貝克·韋瑟斯。
Doug Hansen.
道格·漢森
- Jon Krakauer.
- How're you doing?
- 喬恩·克拉考爾。
- 你怎麼樣？
- Okay.
- Are you...
- 挺好的。
- 你也是嗎？
Krakauer from Outside magazine.
克拉考爾是來自Outside雜誌的。
- Yeah.
- Really?
- 是的
- 真的？
What're you doing?
Writing or climbing or what?
那你來幹嘛？
在這媯央H一起登山？還是幹什麼？
A little bit of both.
差不多就這些吧。
Well. I'll let you know
how the Summit goes, okay?
好吧，我會告訴你我登頂珠峰的，好嗎？
- No need, I'll be there.
- We'll see.
- 不需要了，我也會登頂的。
- 好吧，走著瞧。
What do you do when
you're not climbing, Doug?
道格拉斯，你們不登山的時候在幹嗎？
- What? Work?
- Yeah.
- 什麼？工作嗎？
- 是的
Uh, different things.
Carpenter. Mailman.
恩，各種工作吧。
木匠 郵差
- Carpenter. Mailman.
- Yep.
- 木匠 郵差
- 是的。
- Seriously, you deliver the mail?
- Yep, I deliver the mail.
- 說真的，你真有送過郵件？
- 是的，我有送過郵件。
Mailman on Everest?
珠峰的郵差？
- Hope so.
- Ha ha. I like that.
- 差不多吧。
- 哈哈。我喜歡。
Mailman on Everest.
珠峰郵差。
There we go.
出發吧。
- Beck.
- Yeah.
- 貝克。
- 恩？
You know, he made it to the
South Summit on Everest last year.
你知道嗎，他上年從珠峰南側成功登頂。
- Who? Doug did?
- Yeah.
- 誰？道格拉斯？
- 是啊！
- That's pretty hot for a mailman.
- Yep
- 那這對於一個郵差來說還是挺厲害的。
- 是啊
Brown's Peak,McKinley.
布朗峰 麥金利山
I never made it up to the top of McKinley myself.
我從來也沒有獨自成功登頂麥金利山。
I know.
我知道。
- How did you know that?
- 89', right?
- 你怎麼知道的？
- 89年事，是吧？
Ohhh.
You done your research.
噢~~
你是做足功課的！
That's what we do.
這本來就是我們需要做的。
GARUDA HOTEL
GARUDA 酒店
You, my friends, are following
in some very famous footsteps.
我的朋友們，你將追隨英勇著腳步。
A histroy made famous by George Everest,
時勢造英雄 來自 喬治峰
George Mallory, Tenzing Norgay,
Edmund Hillary...
喬治·馬洛 ，丹增·諾爾蓋，
埃德蒙·希拉
- And Rob Hall.
- lege...
- 還有 羅布·霍爾
- 等等···
- Yeah.
- Oh, yeah.
- 是的！
- 哦，是的！
legend... lege...legends, all of them.
他們··他們··他們都是傳奇人物。
- Ha-ha-ha...Eh ha ha...
-  哈-哈-哈···· 恩 哈 哈····
That's right.
是啊！
For those of you who dare face the dreams,
對於那些敢於面對夢想的人，
Adventure Consultants offer something
beyond the power of words to describe.
探險顧問給了些無以言表的描述話語給我們。
And why don't we
describe it in the brochure.
但為什麼我們不將其寫在冊子上面呢？
Because it's mostly just pain.
因為這個過程大部分都是很痛苦的（需要親歷）。
- Yes.
- Ain't that the truth.
- 是的。
- 這不就是現實嘛。
And the odd,if you don't mind, Mike.
並且奇怪的是，如果麥克你不介意的話。
And the odd missing toe.
你那奇怪的消失了的腳趾。
There we go.
好吧
- Oh.
- Ooo.
- 噢·
To put it simply, guys.
夥計們，簡單來說，
Human beings
simply aren't built to function
我們人類簡單的身體構造不適合
at the cruising altitude of a 747.
在相對於一架747的巡航高度的高度生存。
Okay, once we get above here,
above the South Col.
好，一旦我們到達上面這堙A珠峰南側上面。
Our bodies will be literally dying
and I mean literally dying.
我們的身體將會在理論上來說已經死亡了
我的意思是真的理論上來說會死翹翹。
It's not called the Death Zone
for nothing, guys.
夥計們，這就是我們通常說的死亡區域。
So, the game is,can we get you up to the top
所以，這遊戲的規則就是我們能否帶領你們順利到達頂峰。
and down to the bottom before that happens.
和在出事之前帶領你返回下面來。
- You sure can.
- Oh.
- 你肯定可以。
- 噢
Beck Weathers,ladies and gentlemen.
先生們女士們，這是貝克韋瑟斯。
You might've noticed he's a bit of a lone star state.
你可能已經注意到他有點德州范。
100% Texan right here, people.100% Texan.
我是德克莎斯州人，100%的德州人。
You met Mike Groom.
你見到麥克格隆
I like to introduce you to Andy Harris.
- Or Harold.
我想把你們介紹這是安迪·哈里斯
-或者叫 哈羅德
Harold had got out of Queenstown.
哈羅德離開了皇后鎮
Taranaki actually,originally Canada.
塔拉納基事實上是土生土長加拿大人。
Helen and the rest of the team are already on their way up to Base Camp.
海倫和我團隊的其他人已經在去大本營的路上。
They're setting it up when we get there.
當我們到達大本營的時候，她們應該會把營地紮好。
- Today is March 30th, people.
- Yeah.
- 各位，今天是30月30日。
- 是的。
I plan on going to the Summit, May 10th.
我計劃我們5月10日將會登頂。
It's been a lucky day for me in Adventure Consultants,
從探險顧問團隊來說我們還是比較幸運的
and the weather is usually pretty stable around then.
並且在上面的天氣通常也是比較穩定。
So that means,
這也就意味著，
We have 40 days,to train your bodies and your minds
我們有40天的時間去讓你的體魄和意志去適應
to go for it.
在登頂之前。
Now. I know there is a lot of
mountaineering experience in this room
在此，我也知道在這個房間堶惘釩雃h有經驗的登山者
you wouldn't be here without it.
如果沒有經驗你也不敢來到這堿D戰珠峰。
- Stu, K2, Broad Peak.
- Nice.
- 斯圖峰，K2峰，寬峰
- 厲害。
John Taske,
1192m of Mount Kosciuszko.
約翰也曾登過在海拔1192米的科修斯科山
- Ha ha ha...
- Eh ha ha...
- 哈  哈 哈···
- And Yasuko Namba.
- Oh.
-還有恭子南玻
- 噢
- 6 of the 7 Summits.
- Yeah.
- 登頂7個山峰中的6個
- 是的。
- An amazing woman.
- There you go.
- 一位讓人驚嘆的女士。
- 是的
- Let's make it 7.
- Thank you.
- 來吧，讓我們一起完成挑戰第7座
- 謝謝！
But, Everest though, is another beast.
Another beast altogether.
但是，珠峰是另一頭難以馴服的猛獸，是這7座堶掖抯F害的一頭猛獸。
That's why you're here.Isn't that right, Dougy.
這就是為什麼你會在這，不是嗎？道格拉斯
Oh, yeah.Yeah.
噢，是的。是的。
So, listen.Tonight, that's it for me.
所以，聽著各位，今晚，是屬於我們的。
Eat, drink, be merry.
Tomorrow we trek.
各位盡量吃飽喝足吧，明天我們將會爬山涉水。
Alright, let's go.
好吧，出發吧。
Alright, folks, hang on.
好的，大伙們抓緊了。
Okay.
好的。
That's it.
Here we go, colonel
好的
出發吧，上校。
Alright, everybody, earbuds.
好的，所有人，帶好你的耳塞。
Take your seats.Buckle in, everyone.
找到你們的位置，扣好安全帶，坐好了各位。
Thanks, bud.
謝謝。
Murdock, here we go.
默多克，來吧。
Okay, everybody.
好的，各位。
Hey, can you believe it.
嘿，真神奇。
Lukla : 9,383 ft
2,860 m
盧卡拉峰：9,383英尺
2,860 米
Take it easy.Nice work.
慢慢來，做得好。
Take it easy.
慢慢來。
- Ready.
- Let's go.
- 準備
- 出發
You lead the way.
你來帶路。
- Are you alright?
- Come on, man.
- 你還好嗎？
- 來吧，兄弟。
NAMCHE BAZAAR : 12,303 ft
3,750 m
納姆澤巴扎爾：12303英尺
3750米
Guys, man want to see
your climbing permits.
夥計們，他需要看一下你們的攀登許可證。
Need to see all
your climbing permits.
需要看下你們所有人的攀登許可證。
Thank you very much.We'll see you on the way back.
非常感謝。我們在回程時候再見吧。
Thank you very much.
非常感謝。
- All good?
- Yeah, yeah. Yeah, you?
- 沒問題吧？
- 沒問題，沒問題，你呢？
- Yeah.
- Hey...
- 沒問題
- 嘿···
Thanks, Rob.
謝謝，羅布
- Thanks for what?
- You know, the discount.
- 幹嘛感謝我？
- 你懂的，給我打折。
You're working 3 jobs, Doug.
你在同時做三份工作啊，道格拉斯。
It's the least I can do, right?
這是我僅能做的，不是嗎？
I know you didn't have to do it.
I appreciate it.
我知道你其實不必這樣做。
我非常感謝。
Let's just get you to the top this time.
這次就讓我帶你成功的登頂吧。
- Yeah.
- 恩，好的。
- 好
Yeah.
好
How're you feeling, Beck?
你感覺怎樣貝克？
About a third to midland.
離中部區差不多三分之一。
Come on, buddy.
You can do it.
來吧兄弟，你可以的！
Thought I was going to
acclimatize faster than this.
我以為我會很快的適應這種環境。
Uh.
You'll be alright.
恩。
你會沒事的。
Go on, critters
加油，夥計們。
Woo.
喔···
- Well.
- Yeah.
- 很好
- 恩
How close did you get?
你有過多接近成功登頂？
I got really close,
but...
我已經非常靠近了，只是·····
got a lateness ,pretty shot anyways, so...
只是來的有點遲，反正也是非常靠近了，所以
I think I would have made a run for it.
我想我會為了成功登頂再來一次的。
- Everyday I wake up thinking that.
- Then why didn't you do it?
- 每天我醒來都會想著要成功登頂。
- 那為什麼你不去呢？
Because I turned him around.
因為沒讓他繼續下去。
1:15 (PM) of the South Summit.
下午1：15 主峰南側。
That condition, we weren't going to
make that 2 PM turn around.
在那種登山條件下，我們將無法繼續下去只能在下午2點返回。
It's all good more to make the top, Beck.
雖然沒有比登頂來得更好，貝克。
but you pay me to bring you down safely.
但是你出錢也是要讓我安全帶你回去的。
Remember that.
請你一定要記住這點。
Okay.
好的。
What's eating him?
什麼事情惹他了？
One of those Sherpas is Tenzing.
He had an accident.
其中有個叫丹增的夏爾巴人遇到意外了
- Oh yeah.
- Yeah.
- 噢 好吧
- 恩
... on the icefall.
··· 在冰爆那遇上的意外。
It's not good,had to bring him down.
那時情況很糟糕，所以不得不把他送下去。
TENGOCHE MONASTERY : 12,687 ft
3,867 m
TENGOCHE 修道院 ：12687英尺
3867米
Blessing at Tengboche Monastery
在TENGOCHE 修道院 祈禱
Namaste.
合十禮
THE CLIMBERS' MEMORIALS, THOK LA : 16,000 ft
4,877 metres
THOK LA 攀登者紀念館 : 16,000 英尺
4,877 米
EVEREST BASE CAMP : 17,600 ft
5,367 metres
珠峰大本營：17,600 英尺
5,367 米
Congratulation, you all made it.
Welcome to Base Camp.
恭喜！你們都做到了。歡迎來到大本營。
It'll be a united nations
here this year.
這塈眴n變成一個聯合國了。
We've the Allmax teams.
South africans.
我們有來至南非的Allmax團隊。
And right up here,
並且在這
in the best spot of all,
有全部駐點堶掖怞n的一個地點
we have the Adventure Consultants
Base Camp.
在大本營有我們的探險顧問。
- Hey.
- Hi, Helen.
- 嘿
- 你好，海倫。
- Hi, how are you?
- Nice to see you.
- 你好嗎？
- 很高心見到你。
- Welcome, nice to see you.
- Thank you.
- 歡迎，很高心見到你。
- 謝謝
- Hi, Rob.
- Hey.
- 你好，羅布。
- 嘿
- You alright?
- Yeah, yeah, good. You?
- 你還好？
- 恩，挺好的。你呢？
- Yeah. You know, we're good.
- Yeah, it looks good.
- 恩，你知道的，我們都挺好。
- 是的，看起來還不錯。
For those of you that haven't met.
好像沒見過你？
This is Helen Wilton,
Base Camp manager.
這是海倫威爾頓，大本營的管理員。
She'll be your mom
for the next... few weeks.
在接下來的幾周埵o將會是你的「媽媽」。
Any problems take it to her,
and she'll sort it.
有什麼問題就找她吧，她會搞定的。
Alright.
Um.
好的
恩
Well, it's very nice to finally
meet you all in person.
很高興終於可以在人群中見到你。
Ang Dorjee, come here.
昂多吉，過來。
This is Ang Dorjee, everyone.
各位，這是昂多吉。
He's you climbing sirdar,your lead sherpa.
他是你們的登山隊長，你們的夏爾巴領隊。
- Hey, how are you?
- Okay.
- 嘿 你好嗎？
- 很好。
- You... You speak English?
- Better than you, Mr. America.
- 你···你講英語嗎？
- 講得比你還好，「美國先生」。
- Bet you climb better than I do, huh?
- Yeah.
- 打賭你登山也得比我好，哈？
- 是啊
- Yeah.
Ang summit it 3 times, Beck.
安格登頂三次，貝克。
Alright, alright.
I hear you, I hear you.
好，好，好。
我聽你的，我聽你的。
Alright. Well, there's tea in the mess tin
好的，在飯盒堶惘陳龤C
when you dumped your sacks.
And...
你可以放下你的背囊。
還有···
The comm's tent down the back.
通訊帳篷在回去一點的地方。
That's the cooking tent
and over there
那邊是炊事帳篷和在那邊···
- is the toilet.
- All good?
-  是廁所
- 全都都能用嗎？
It's a little bit drafty,
but just remember that...
這廁所通風還是不錯的，只是你需要記住···
When the wind gets
upheave, you got
當風吹起來的時候，你就可以
the same view as
George Everest did.
看到佐治峰那樣相同的景色。
For those of you who haven't
used crampons before
對於之前沒曾用過指冰爪的人
left and right are mark
you can't get it wrong.
左右是有標記的，你就不會弄錯了。
- Alright, so, simple.
- Okay.
- 好的，就這麼簡單。
- 可以吧。
First of all, you push it
into the shoe, like this.
首先，你需要像這樣將它套進鞋子。
Unbelievable.
難以置信。
If it isn't the
mayor of Base Camp.
如果他不是大本營的營長。
Scott Fischer,
Mr. Mountain Madness.
斯科特·菲捨爾，瘋狂登山先生。
In the flesh.
在曬太陽啊。
You want a cup?
要喝一杯嗎？
Sit down, man.
Acclimatize.
坐下吧兄弟，來嘗嘗！
Okay. I'm normally a tea man myself, but...
好吧。雖然我自認為是個比較懂茶的人，但是···
- Let's give it a go.
- Thank you so much.
- 就來一杯吧。
- 非常感謝。
Well, it's crazy this year, aye.
恩，今年登山季真瘋狂
I know, man.
兄弟，我懂。
Some idiot kiwi goes and
advance Himalaya guide here.
一些愚蠢的新西蘭人和喜馬拉雅發展指導員也來這了
Look what happens.
看這情況
Yeah. Didn't take you too long to get in on the act.
是的，不過這樣的事情不會花你太多的時間的。
Got to make a living, man.
得謀生啊兄弟。
You... went ahead and
fixed the ice post, I see.
我知道你···先行上來和修理了這些冰桿。
Yeah, yeah.It's pretty messy up there this year.
是的，是的。今年那堿O有點亂。
- Yeah?
- The vasses are pretty big.
-  是嗎？
-  vasses 這地方也是挺大的。
Strung 4 or 5 ladders across.
需要捆好4、5個穿行梯子。
You use good ropes there, did you?
你是用好的繩子捆的嗎？
You ready?
Okay.
你準備好了？
好了
This is April 7th
about 10:30 am
今天是4月7日上午10:30左右
This is Sandy Hill Pittman reporting
for Nbc Interactive Media
這是桑迪山皮特曼向NBC互動媒體發去的報導
and we are official at Everest Base Camp.
我們已經正式到達了珠峰大本營
- She one of yours?
- Oh, yeah.
-她是你們的成員之一？
-哦，是的。
Someone went and stole my journalist so I had to get another one.
因為有人挖了我的記者所以我不得不去找其他的。
She's a lot easier on the eye than Jon Krakauer, that's for sure.
可以肯定的是，她比喬恩·克拉考爾要機靈些。
Listen, just to be clear I didn't steal your journalist.
聽著，我只是想說清楚，我沒有挖你記者。
Hey, man.
It's all good.
嘿，兄弟。這沒事。
- Outside magazine gave me a call...
- Hey.
- Outside雜誌打給我···
- 嘿
- They gave me a call...
- Hey!
- 是他們打給我···
- 嘿！
- said they wanted...
- It's all good.
- 說他們想···
- 真的沒事·
they're going to sent a journalist up the hill
他們想送一位記者到山頂
and asked me if I was interested.
然後問我是否有興趣帶他上去
It was his call in the end.
這是他最後打給我說的
Alright.Carol Mackenzie, team doctor.
好的，這是卡羅爾·麥肯齊，隊醫。
Why don't you kick it off, Carol.
那就開始吧，卡羅爾。
- Hi, everyone.
- Hey, Carol.
- 各位好
- 嘿，卡羅爾
Hi, there.
各位好
- Hey, sorry.
- No, it's fine.
- 嘿，不好意思。
- 沒事
Um. So...
Rob and Harold and Mike
恩，那··這是羅布、哈羅德和麥克。
will tell you all sorts of stuff
about mountaineering.
我們將會盡量簡明扼要地將一些登山的東西告訴大家
but, from a medical stand of point,
但，從一個隊醫的角度來說，
getting you to the top of Everest
was really about oxygen.
把你們帶上珠峰山頂的關鍵是足夠氧氣。
and the lack of it.
而上面是很缺氧的。
To give you the best chance of summiting,
為了把握好最佳的登頂機會
you need to prepare your bodies for the thin air up there.
你需要讓你的身體適應這媯}薄的空氣的狀態
So, over the next month before the final ascend,
所以，在下個月最後的攀登之前
you are going to make 3 partial acclimatizing ascends,
你將需要進行3個部分的適應性攀登，
returning here, to Base Camp,after each one.
逐一完成，然後回到大本營這堙C
The bad news is that each ascend begins and ends with the icefall.
壞消息是伴隨著我們每次攀登的開始和結束都會經過冰爆
I'm sorry,but there's no way around it.
我很遺憾，但這堥S有其他路可以繞過去了。
There're millions of tons of glacier ice continue moving day and night.
這兒有數百萬噸冰川冰日夜在持續移動。
Your crevasses so deep they probably don't even have a bottom.
你面對的冰川裂縫非常深，他們甚至沒能見到底
It is not a place that you want to get caught hanging out in,
那是一個你掉下去就別想再爬上來的地方
especially when the sun hits it.
特別是當陽光曬到冰川上面的時候
So, we're going to be up, nice and early and through that as soon as possible.
所以，我們將盡可能需要輕巧、小心地盡早盡快地通過那堙C
Now, the Sherpas are going ahead and
fixed the ladders across the crevasses
現在，夏爾巴人將預先修復冰川裂縫中的通行梯。
and we've made it
as safe as we possibly can.
我們需要盡可能安全地通過
But, that is not to say
that it is completely safe.
但是，這很難說是百分百的安全。
19 people have died in that icefall.
有19人曾死在這力度冰爆中。
- Whoa whoa whoa...
- Hold on.
- 哇~~~哇~~~哇~~~
- 抓緊。
Steady.
穩住。
- You alright, Jon?
- You alright?
-喬恩你還好嗎？
-你還好嗎？
- I'm good. Okay.
- Alright, steady up.
- 我還行，沒事
- 好的，平穩地站起來。
So, remember,we're a team,
所以，請記住，我們是一個團隊。
let's look up for each other.
我們需要相互幫忙。
- Lookout for hypothermia.
(CAMP ONE : 19,500 ft  : 5,944 m)
- 注意保暖
（一號營地：19500英尺：5944米）
Things like slur speech and irrational behaviour.
像傳聞說的那些故事和一些非理智的行為。
I've seen hypoxia climbers ripped off all their clothes
我曾看過缺氧的登山者脫掉他們的衣服
at 8000 m because they are feeling hot.
因為他們感覺熱在海拔8000米。
You all know about cerebral edema,the swelling of your brain
你們都知道腦水腫吧，你的大腦會腫脹
to the point of lost of motor function and eventually death.
並且逐步失去運轉最終死亡。
And pulmonary edema, which is your lungs filling with fluid.
同時肺水腫也會使你的肺充滿液體。
till you fatally drown.
直到你不行了為止。
The only cure is to get down the mountain fast.
唯一可以救活的方法就是盡可能快地送下山
- Alright. Okay.
- Alright, buddy.
- 好的
- 好的，各位。
But, it is not all doom and gloom here, okay?
但是，這也不意味著這堥麭B是厄運和墳墓好吧？
Myself and the whole AC team are here to make sure you get up and down safely
我個人和整個AC團隊都會在這婼T保大家順利登山和安全返回
and you will acclimatize naturally.
而你們也會逐步適應
So, why don't we all,give Carol a nice big thank you.
那現在我們用掌聲來給卡羅爾一個感謝吧。
- Oh, you don't have to give me that.
- It's her first time here.
- 哦，大家不必感謝我。
- 這也是她第一次來這堙C
- Hey.
- Alright.
- 嘿
- 好的。
Nice job.
做得好
April 23rd
4月23日
CAMP TWO : 21,300 ft
6,492 m
2號營地：21300英尺 6492米
- Well done.
- Have a seat.
- 做得好
- 來坐下
You want to get on the regulator
or you want to hear that
你想進行調整下或者你想聽下
Can you get hosed.
你可以先洗下
- Yasuko.
- Beck.
-Yasuko
-貝克
- How're you doing, darling?
- Okay.
- 你還好嗎？
- 還好
- Good?
- Yeah.
-還好？
-是的
- Well done.
- Hang in there.
- 做得好
- 堅持住
Help yourself with that.
自己來吧
In a situation like this,
you just want to catch your breath
在這樣一種情況，你只會像盡量呼吸
go right up to 4, you should
start feeling pretty good.
去到4號營地，你就應該會開始感覺不錯了
Yeah, I can feel that already.
是的，我已經有點適應了
How did you boys go?
你們幾個怎樣？
- Instant happiness.
- Hey.
- 瞬間感到幸福
- 嘿
- Amazing.
- Very happy.
- 真好
- 非常開心
- Doug, you okay?
- Huh?
- 達格拉斯，你還好？
- 恩？
When we get back to base,
I want you to...
回到大本營後，我想你去
get Carol to get
a look at you.
去卡羅爾那去讓她看看你的情況
Nah, I'm alright.
I'm okay.
不用了，我沒問題
我很好呢！
Then... do me a favor,
swinge another oxygen.
那···幫我個忙，多吸吸氧氣。
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
- 好嗎？
- 好
- You got enough?
- We got plenty.
- 你有足夠的氧氣？
- 我多著呢。
Alright.
那就好
Get some tea in here.
在這喝些茶
Just lift your shirt up a bit.
把你的襯衫拉高一點
Thank you.
謝謝
Now, take a deep breath for me.
現在，深呼吸一下
Just take one of those
in the morning
早上的時候吃一片
with a little bit of water
before breakfast.
在早餐前用熱水服
Okay. thanks.
好的，謝謝
- Right, Beck. You're up.
- Sorry.
- 好了，貝克。準備好了。
- 不好意思
Yeah.
Go for it.
好的，來吧。
Read it and weep.
把一下脈
Take it easy there.
慢慢來不用急
- Right, you can stop.
- Yeah?
- 好了 你可以停下了
- 好了？
- You're in great shape, Beck.
- I'm in great shape.
- 你狀態挺好的貝克
- 我狀態挺好？
- Yeah.
- 6 days a week in the gym
- 是的
- 一星期去6天健身房
- ought to do it.
- Your wife must have love that.
- 應該狀態會不錯的
- 你妻子一定很喜歡你經常去健身房
Yeah, she does.
是的，她確實挺喜歡。
Oh no.
What's the date today?
噢不，今天是幾號？
- April 25th.
- No.
- 4月25日
- 不
No.
不
I need to send a message to my wife.
Can I use your fax?
我需要給我妻子發個信息。
我可以用你的傳真嗎？
You might want to look at this one first,
came in for you last night.
你可能想先看看這個，昨天晚上傳來的。
Happy Anniversary Beck
- Peach.
結婚週年紀念日快樂 貝克
- 桃子
Lord.
天啊
What?
怎麼了？
Can I-Can I use your satphone?
我可以用下你的衛星電話嗎？
Woo. Well, if this did come in
last night, it is an emergency.
喔，好吧，如果這確實是昨晚來的消息那應該是很緊急的
- It's...  25 bucks a minute, Beck.
- Yeah, fine.
- 25美元一分鐘 貝克
- 好的，沒問題。
- No. This one is on us.
- Seriously.
- 不，這次就算我們的吧。
- 真的嗎？
Thanks.
謝謝
Rob.
羅布
- Beck?
- Peach, it's me.
- 貝克？
- 桃子，是我。
What happened?
怎麼了？
Nothing. Nothing.
I'm fine.
沒，沒什麼。
我很好
Where-Where are you?
你，你在哪呢？
I'm at Base Camp right now.
我現在在珠峰大本營
You're calling me from Everest?
你在珠峰給我打電話？
Yeah, it's a satellite phone, honey.
是的，是用衛星電話得給你的寶貝。
Oh my god.
How much is that costing?
噢，我的天啊。
這不很貴嗎？
- What's the problem?
- There is no problem, Peach.
- 這有什麼問題嗎？
- 這沒什麼問題，桃子。
I'm sorry, we were
up at Camp 2 and
我很抱歉，我們去了2好營地
that's why I didn't send
you a fax yesterday.
所以我昨天無法給你發傳真
Happy anniversary.
Okay.
結婚週年紀念日快樂！
好的！
- Get off.
- Mom.
- 走開
- 媽媽
- How're the kids?
- Fine.
- 孩子們怎樣？
- 他們很好
- Hey.
- Peach.
- 嘿
- 桃子
- Get off.
- Bud's here.
- 走開
- 巴德在這
Doing his homework
in the morning as per usual.
像往常一樣在早上做他的功課
You want to say hi to him?
你想跟他聊兩句嗎？
Yeah, of course I do.
好啊，當然想。
- Hang on.
- Okay.
- 等等
- 好的
- Say hi.
- Hey, Dad.
- 打聲招呼
- 嘿，爸爸
- Hey, Bud.
- Hi.
- 嘿 巴德
- 嘿
I miss you, buddy.
我挺想念你小伙子
Oh, and Meg went
on her first date.
噢，對了，梅格去了她的初次約會
- Mom.
- ...last weekend. Well, you did.
- 媽媽~~
-···上週末的。嘿，妳確實去了。
- Wow. Really?
- Um-hum.
- 哇，真的？
- 恩恩~
- Get off.
- Peach.
- 走開
- 桃子
I missed you, honey.
我想念你寶貝。
Mom?
Mom.
媽媽~媽媽~
Missed the kids...
也想念孩子們···
a lot.
非常想念
Peach.
桃子
Listen, I got to get
the kids to school.
好吧，我需要送孩子們去學校了
So, I got to run.
我要掛電話了
Okay.
好吧
Yeah.
Go careful.
恩，注意安全啊。
Bye bye.
拜 拜
Is Dad okay?
爸爸還好嗎？
Just... he never calls.
只是···他從來不打電話的。
He's...
他····
I think he's scared.
我覺得他是有點怕了
? It's going nowhere
on the mantlepiece ?
? Well, do I lie like
a loungeroom lizard ?
Yeah.
Beck.
Come in mate, come on.
貝克。進來夥計，進來。
- Come on.
- Come on, Beck.
- 來吧
- 進來吧，貝克。
You don't dance.
You don't climb.
你不跳舞，也不爬山。
Come on, guys.
Beck Weathers.
來吧，夥計們。
貝克韋瑟斯
- Yeah.
- Come on, Beck. Come on.
-來吧，貝克，來吧
- Go dance.
- Go go.
- 一起跳舞
-  來~來~
? ... take the weather with you ?
? Everywhere you go,
always take the weather,
the weather with you ?
Hey, man.
Breaking into the rations?
嘿，兄弟
搶奪配給了嗎？
Yeah, you want some?
是啊，要來杯嗎？
No. I'll...
I'll wait till we summit.
不了，等登頂後再喝吧。
I don't know about that, Neal.
尼爾，我搞不懂你
We'll get there.
我們會到達頂峰的
I'm excited.
我現在很興奮
Anyway, me and Anatoli are here
to help you, you know.
反正無論如何我和阿納托利都會幫你的，你知道的。
It's too much competition, Anatoli.
阿納托利，這有太多的挑戰了
We don't need competition
between people.
我們不需要人與人之間的挑戰
This competition, between
every person and this mountain.
這次是每個人和這座山之間的挑戰
The last word always
belongs to the mountain.
遺言總是屬於這座山的
LHOTSE FACE : 12,400 ft
7,132 m
洛子峰：12400英尺 7132米
- Ang Dorjee.
- Yeah!
- 昂多吉
- 好的！
Stay there, Beck.
Stay there.
呆在這，貝克。
呆在這
Okay, I'm coming down.
好的，我現在下來。
Harold, Mike.
The rope.
哈羅德、邁克繩子
This isn't happening, guys.
這不會發生的，夥計們。
Let's turn him around.
來把他轉過來
Get him off the Face,
and back to the Base Camp
把他的臉轉過來，把他送回大本營
Turn around.
轉身
Ang Dorjee. Come on,
we're going down.
昂多吉 過來
我們現在下去
Okay.
好的
My hands!
我的雙手！
Okay, make a fist again.
Just kind of keep clenching
好的，再次握拳
握緊
to keep the blood flow.
這樣保持血液流通
What's going on, man?
怎麼呢夥計？
Still waiting for the south Africans.
還需要等下南非團隊
Taiwanese took forever as well.
台灣人團隊也到了
Hey, Ian.
You haven't paid for these ladders.
嘿 伊恩
你過這座梯還沒給錢呢！
Yeah, yeah.
Your yak fun money is coming.
好~好~
等下就給你你的犛牛假幣。
- You serious man?
- Come on. Get a move on.
- 你認真的兄弟？
- 擺脫，快過來吧。
- How long you're been waiting him?
- A good 45 minutes.
- 你還要等多久？
- 45分鐘
- Man, it's freezing.
- Yeah.
- 兄弟，我快凍僵了。
- 好的
- Stinging, huh?
- Yeah.
- 刺痛吧？
- 是的
- Hey, Rob, we got to get him over!
- We're working on it.
- 嘿 羅布，我們需要送他過去！
- 我們在處理了。
He's freezing, man.
他快凍僵了兄弟
- Are you set?
- Yeah.
- 設置好了？
- 是的
- We're sending him over, mate.
- Do it.
- 我們現在送他過去，夥計。
- 來吧
Keep going, Beck.
向前走，貝克
Looking good.
看起來不錯
- That's it.
- Now, head up, mate. Head up.
- 就這樣
- 現在，抬頭 夥計 抬頭
Hold on, Beck!
穩住 貝克！
- Whoaaaa.
- Pull. Pull.
-哇~~~~~
-拉~~ 拉~~
Help. Help!
Help!
救命！救命！
救命！
Beck, you alright?
貝克，你還好嗎？
Are these ladders
going to take 2.
這些梯子好像不太行了
Yeah. I'll get a rope.
I'll belay you, okay!
好吧，我去拿些繩子，我會紮住你，好的！
- Stay right where you are, mate.
- I can't pull yourself up!
- 在那個地方別動，夥計
- 你自己得起來，我無法拉你上來。
I'm going to
come after you.
我準備過去你那
Good-Good, Beck.
You're okay.
好-好，貝克。
你很不錯
Untie these,
you got to tie me in.
綁緊這，你把我綁緊了。
Come and get me.
過來救我
- On belay.
- Got it, on belay.
- 在綁了
- 綁緊了
Let's go.
去了
I'm coming after you, Beck.
Here I come, mate.
我現在過去，貝克
我現在來了夥計
Nice and easy,
慢慢來
- I can't feel my hands!
- Looking good.
- 我的手沒感覺了！
- 沒事沒事
Help me.
過來救我
- Beck. Beck. Beck.
- Help me!
- 貝克 貝克 貝克
- 救我
Stay right where you are, mate.
呆在那別亂動
- Can't pull myself up.
- I'm right here. I'm here.
- 我無法起身
- 我在這，我在這
I can't pull myself up!
我起不來了
I got you.
我捉住你了
You okay?
你還好嗎？
No guarantees to the Summit.
I get it.
不是說好的帶我登上峰頂嗎？
我卻到如此田地
I can get killed because
I'm waiting in line.
因為我呆在這線上，害我我快要完蛋了
Like I'm in a freaking Wal-mart.
搞得我像在怪物一樣的沃爾瑪
Not while I paid you $65,000
我不會支付你$65,000
Now get me off of here.
如果現在帶我離開這
That's it.
Plant your feet, one at a time.
就這樣，一步一步走。
Alright, thanks for coming by.
(Meeting for guides, organizers)
好的，感謝各位過來。
（組織者、指引者會議）
Look. Base Camp as you know
is chalked up all this year, so...
各位，像你所瞭解一樣，大本營
I think it'll
all benefit us greatly
我認為這對我們都非常有好處
by coming together like this
and you know,
我們像這樣聚在一起進行溝通
working out some kind
of plan and schedule.
然後按計劃和時間表行事
- What, like some kind of rotor?
- Yes.
-什麼，像「輪子」一樣運轉？
-是的
On Everest.
在珠峰
Everyone knows Everest is a business
for you, Rob, but are you kidding?
每個人都知道珠峰就像是你的生意，但你現在卻在開玩笑？
What gives you the right to tell us
when we can climb and when we can't.
是誰給你的權力來告訴我們什麼時候能爬什麼時候不能怕？
I'm not telling you, man.
I'm asking.
我沒有在命令各位，兄弟
我只是在請求
If we know when everybody is
planning to summit, for instance...
如果我們知道大家都計劃什麼時候登頂，
You know we can avoid the chaos
that happened at the Icefall today.
你知道我們有能力避免今天在冰爆發生的混亂情況
Adventure Consultants
are aiming for May 10th.
冒險顧問提議是5月10日
So are we, man.
我們也是，兄弟
- Us too.
- May 10th.
- 我們也是
- 5月10日
Okay, that's bumper to bumper traffic on the Hillary step.
好吧，在希拉堮|要萬無一失。
Yes it is, that's my point.
是的，這是我的觀點
Look, this is ridiculous.
We summiting when we want.
嘿，這很可笑，我們喜歡什麼時候登頂就什麼時候登頂
Alright. And I don't need
your permission to climb the mountain.
可以了嗎？並且我不需要你的批准才能爬這座山
Ian, have you seen how
many people are here
艾恩，你看今年有這麼多人在這
- ... at Base Camp this year.
- We're finish here.
- ···在大本營
- 就這樣吧
- Come on, lads.
- Hey, man.
- 來吧
- 嘿，兄弟
Ah.
Come in, man.
哈
進來兄弟。
- Hi.
- Ha ha.
-你好
-哈 哈
- Have a drink, Rob.
- Yeah, have a drink.
- 來喝一杯，羅布
- 好，喝一杯
Na zdorovye. (*To health.)
祝健康
- Nostrovia.  (*Cheers)
- 乾杯
- With a word. Yeh.
- Um-hum.
- 有話說？
- 恩恩
- You're a little crook, huh.
- I know, it's just a little.
- 你就像是個「小騙子」，
- 我知道，這有點··
- A little touch of the deli belly.
- He means Buddha belly.
- 肚子有點漲
- 他那是佛肚
What's going on Roberto?
怎麼了羅伯特？
I don't like the look of the
crowds on the ropes.
我不喜歡那擁擠的人群
We ran into some trouble
once we're above Camp 3.
有一次我們在上面3號營地遇上些麻煩。
Well. You want to top
on the 10th, yeah?
你想10號登上峰頂是嗎？
- Yeah.
- So do I.
- 是的
- 我也想
What're you saying,
we should team up?
你想說什麼？
我們要一起行進？
Well, it's an idea, yeah.
我有個想法
Oh, man.
哦 兄弟
Oh, I don't know, man.
哦 我不知道兄弟 。
We have different styles, man.
Like...
我們兩都登山模式都不同，兄弟
All due respect,
you're a hand holder.
你就想個一把手，備受尊重。
I mean the best, but...
我的意思是你是最好的，但是···
I just believe that if you can't
get up there yourself
我只是相信，如果你無法自己站起來
you shouldn't be on
the mountain at all.
你就永遠也不應該踏上這座山
You guide your team,
I guide my.
你帶領你的團隊，我帶領我的團隊。
I'm just suggesting that we work
with each other instead of against.
我只是建議我們應該相互合作而不是相互對抗。
The only way we both summit, mate,
is that we work together.
合作是我們大家都能登頂的唯一方法兄弟。
Particularly fixing the ropes.
特別是我們需要擰成一股繩
It's got to make sense.
這樣做才有意義
Ah.
恩
Why not.
好吧
- Oh Yeah.
- Yeah, I see the sense in it.
- 好吧
- 恩，你說的很對
Okay then.
就這樣定了
- Thanks, Scott.
- Alright.
- 謝了，斯科特
- 不用謝
Who's going to lead when we get up there.
當我們登到上面的時候隨來引領
Rob, if I say I want to lead,could it be done?
羅布，如果說我想讓我來帶路的話，你覺得可行嗎？
- Whoa whoa whoa.
- Okay, hey.
- 喔~喔~喔~
- 好的 嘿
You got to work with Ang Dorjee.
'cause we're working together now.
我們現在已經是共同協作了所以你也需要和昂多吉一起合作
He's just saying if both of us...
Whoa whoa whoa whoa.
他剛不是說如果我們···
喔~喔~喔~
Okay.
好了
Ang Dorjee.
昂多吉
We're all professionals here.
我們全部都是專業的
We work together and we get the job done.
我們需要風雨同舟一起登頂
- Yes?
- Alright, yeah.
- 是嗎？
- 當然
We're planning of stashing,what 8 bottles of "O"
我們的潛在計劃是，配備8瓶的氧氣
over the South Summit.
然後從山峰的南面越過
- Well, I'm not using "O".
- What do you mean?
- 哇~我不打算用氧氣瓶
- 那你打算怎樣？
- You're not using oxygen at all?
- Come on man, you know you want it.
- 你打算全程都不用氧氣瓶？
- 少來吧兄弟，你肯定要用的
In his health, don't need it.
對於他的身體條件來說，是不需要用到的
Yeah, but Anatoli,you're guiding for Scott this year.
是的，但阿納托利，這次你是為斯科特做引導
You have people's lives in your hands. It's a job.
你手上掌握著大家的命運，這是你該帶上氧氣瓶的。
Never used it.Never will.
我從來不用氧氣瓶，從來不用。
Bigger problems if you run out.
如果你依賴氧氣瓶且一旦用光麻煩就大了。
Okay.
好吧
I'll put some more bottles of "O" up there.
我會帶多點氧氣瓶上去的
- You know, that would be good.
- Alright.
-放心吧，會順利的。
-好吧
Just as long as you guys are clear.
只是讓各位清楚
You work for me you use oxygen,otherwise you don't work for me.
如果你是我團隊的就必須用上氧氣瓶
Hey, you don't have to ask me.
嘿，這個我懂
I've been up here before without "O"s, Rob.
I don't need to deal with clients.
我之前上去也沒帶氧氣瓶羅布，我也不需要和客戶打交道
- Alright. Next we have the fixed ropes.
- Yeah.
- 好吧，接下來我們需要固定好那些攀登繩
- 好的
Particularly, above the Lhotse Face.
特別是在洛子峰上面的
You let us start make new fixed rope.
你是讓我們開始去重新固定繩子吧
- And Southeast Ridge as well.
- Yes, it does.
- 還有東南嶺的也是
- 好的
Well. My idea is that we work together
好吧，我的想法是我們共同協作
and we fix ropes together,we share the duties.
一起去固定攀登繩和風雨同舟
- Okay.
- Sounds good.
- 好的
- 聽起來不錯
Alright, you and Lopsang
maybe get together,
好的，你和Lopsang 應該一起
talk about who want to fix what and where, okay?
互相討論下誰該做什麼，好嗎？
Ah.Only essentials.
好了，只帶必須的
I'm not going to tell you what to pack,
but be brutal, okay.
雖然有點不講理但是我是不會告訴你應該帶什麼不要帶什麼的好吧。
1 pound down here is like 10 up there.
這堶咫@磅的東西帶上你就會讓你覺得十磅那麼重的
Light and fast.Light and fast.
輕裝上陣，輕裝上陣。
What, and just like that
you-you killed my summit cappuccino.
什麼，這麼說搞得我連登頂後的珍珠奶茶都沒得喝了！
Go go go.Run.
走 快走~ 你快跑吧~
That camera is totally daine.
( May 5th )
這相機就跟戴恩一樣
（5月5日）
Alright, it's going to be a tough week.
( May 5th )
好吧，接下來將是最煎熬的一周
（5月5日）
But, it's going to be the best Friday of your lives.
但這也將是你們度過的最棒的週五吧
Hey, what-what are we doing in a boat?
嘿，那句叫什麼同舟什麼？
- Summiting!
- Summiting...!
- 登頂！登頂！登頂！
- Now it's up to me, right?
- Yeah, you.
- 好吧現在到我了是嗎？
- 是的到你了
I take 3.
我抽三張
- It's from Jan.
- You can't look at my card.
- 抽簡的
- 你不可以抽我的牌
I knew it was going to be a girl.
我就知道應該是個女孩
I can't believe it.
真是難以置信
It's a girl!
是個女孩！
- Yeah!
- That's great.
- 真的！
- 那太好了！
Alright, good on you.
好的，恭喜你啊！
I know. I knew.
I knew she was.
我就知道，我之前就認識她。
- Thank you. Thank you, Doug.
- Cheers, mate.
- 謝謝，謝謝，道格拉斯
- 來乾杯夥計。
When is she due?
預計什麼時候回去看她？
Mid July.As soon as I get back.
七月中旬吧，一會去就去看她。
- You can't leave now, buddy.
- Yeah, that's true.
- 你現在可不能走啊兄弟
- 是啊
Hey, Rob.
嘿，羅布
Yeah?
恩？
Jan doesn't mind you being here?
你在這簡不擔心你嗎？
Oh oh.Krakauer's sword is unleashed.
噢，噢。開弓沒有回頭箭嘛。
It's okay. I'm...Jan's a climber, Jon. She gets it.
沒事的，簡也是登山隊的，她懂的。
- Oh yeah?
- She is, Helen.
- 噢 真的？
- 是真的
Now you, Doug.What about your wife?
輪到你了道格拉斯。你老婆擔心你嗎？
Oh, she's been fine with it
ever since we divorced.
噢，都離婚了也沒什麼好擔心的
- She's been great with everything since then.
- I'm so sorry, buddy.
- 離婚之後她過得好好的
- 不好意思兄弟
- Oh, no, don't
- I'm sorry.
- 沒·沒事
- 抱歉
No no no.
I asked because
不用·不用
我之所以這樣問是因為
Peach said to me, "If you climb
1 more mountain, I will divorce you."
桃子跟我說，「如果你敢再去爬山，我就跟你離婚。」
And you went ahead
and then booked this trip.
那你不是還繼續來這了嘛。
- Oh.
- Ow...
- 噢
- 哇
No no no. The worst-The worst part of it is that, I...
不 不 不。這··這最麻煩的是，我····
I kind of forgot to tell her.
我卻忘了告訴她我來這了
- No.
- Ha ha ha.
- 不
- 哈哈哈
I forgot to tell her.I did.
我真的忘記告訴她了。
Alright.It's all on the table here.
好吧。那就敞開心扉吧
It hurts. It's dangerous.
It...
這個旅程又煎熬又危險
destroys relationships.
It's costing you all a small fortune.
甚至破壞和家人的關係，還得花錢。
- Were there any negative aspects?
- Yeah.
- 還有什麼比這個壞的？
- 是的
Come on, I got to ask the question.
You know I do.
來吧，你們都知道我為什麼會這樣說的。
Why?
為什麼？
Because
因為
- Because it's there!
- It's there!
- 因為這就是珠穆朗瑪峰
- 這就是挑戰
- 這就是人生
That's why.Thank you Mr. Mallory.
這就是為什麼要來這堙A謝謝馬洛堨生
Come on, guys,I'm-I'm serious.
來吧大伙們，我是很認真的。
- Yasuko.
- Huh?
- Yasuko
- 恩？
Why are you climbing Everest?
為什麼你要來怕珠峰？
Uh.
額。
I'm 47 years old.
我已經47歲了。
I have reached 6 of the 7 summits.
也已經登過了7座當中的6座了。
So. Of course, now I have to reach the 7th.
所以，我當然希望完成第七座登頂。
- It's not an answer.
- Oh.
- 這不是真正的原因吧
- 噢
Why...
No, why any summits?
為什麼··不，為什麼非珠峰不選？
- Well. I...
- Doug.
- 好吧，我
- 道格拉斯·
Why?
為什麼？
- Come on. Tell him about the kids.
- What.
- 來吧，跟他講講那個男孩的事情。
- 什麼
- Tell him about the kids.
- Yeah.
- 跟他講講那個男孩。
- 好吧
- Oh. I...
- You have kids?
- 噢，我···
- 你有孩子？
Yeah, I have kids.
But...
是的，我有個孩子
但是····
I thought I told you their's...their elementary school back home.
我想我有告訴過你他們··他們從小學回家後
I've been going and talking to the kids there and they
我去跟我的孩子講了些這堛漕き
actual helped me raised some of the money to come and...
他們就幫我攢了些來這堛爾艨O和····
gave me a flag to plant on the Summit and...
給了一面讓我登頂後插上的旗
so, I was thinking maybe it's...
所以，我想這也許是····
they see an...a regular guy can,
you know, follow impossible dreams.
他們覺得一個··一個循規蹈矩的人也可以追尋他遙不可及的夢想吧。
Maybe they will be inspired to do the same, I guess.
也許他們也同樣從這件事上得到鼓勵吧我想。
I'm climbing Mount Everest because I can.
我行故我在
Because, to be able to climb that high and
see that kind of beauty nobody ever sees,
因為，我可以登上高峰去看到別人看不到的風景
it'll be a crime not to.
這不是什麼人都可以做到的
Yeh yeh, Dougy.
是的，道格拉斯
- There you go.
- I like that.
- 說得好
- 我喜歡
Hello.
你好
Hey.
Did I wake you?
嘿。
我吵醒你了？
No.
沒有
I did to, you liar.
我知道是吵醒你了，別騙我。
- You okay?
- Yeah.
- 你還好？
- 還好
Yeah yeah, I'm good.
I'm better. I'm better now.
是的 我很好
我覺得狀態更好了現在
I missed you.
我很想你
We go for the final ascend tomorrow.
我們明天就會去進行最後攀登
Oh. So, you're...you summit on Friday?
噢，所以，你···你會在星期五登頂？
Yeah.10th.
是的，10號
- It's your lucky day.
- It is.
- 那是你的幸運日
- 是的
How's the weather?
那堣悎薽蝻芊H
It's good.
天氣很好
Yeah, I think we're going to get a good window.
是的，我覺得我們將會遇上個很好的窗口期
- So... It's a girl.
- Oh yeah.
- 所以··寶貝是個女孩
- 噢是的
And, did you go to the doctor?
Did you get your scan done?
那你有去看醫生嗎？
有去做掃瞄嗎？
- Did you see her?
- Yes, we're good.
- 你看到她的樣子嗎？
- 是的，我們都挺好。
And?
Come on, what does she look like?
然後？
來吧，告訴我她長得怎樣？
Oh, you know.
Blonde hair, nice smile.
噢，你懂的。
金髮碧眼，可愛的笑容。
Perfect height-weight ratio,she's going to be a great climber.
完美的身體比例，她以後應該是個很好的登山運動員。
She's there, Rob...
already.
她已經準備著出生了，羅布···
- Wow.
- Me and you.
- 喔。
- 我和你
And a little bear, huh.
還有一頭「小熊」，哈哈
And in one day,
在某天，
you,me,
你，我
and our little Sarah, we'll all
go climbing together. Huh.
和我們的小莎拉，我們一起去登山。
Sarah?
莎拉？
Yeah.
What do you think?
恩。
你覺得怎樣？
- No way.
- Come on.
- 不好
- 就這樣吧
- No.
- Please, think about it.
- 不
- 好好考慮考慮
- No.
- Huh.
- 不要
- 哈
- You're still there?
- Of course I'm still here.
- 你還在嗎？
- 當然我在聽著呢。
I love you.
我愛你
I love you too.
我也愛你
Sleep well, my love.
好好休息，我的愛人。
Alright.
Bye.
好的
拜
* Everest climbers
Puja blessing ceremony
* 珠峰登山者
火供祈福儀式
Take it easy now,you're going to be okay.
慢慢來，你會沒事的。
Okay, we're going to get you down the hill. Alright.
好的，我們準備把你送下山好吧。
Hey, Neal.
You okay?
嘿，尼爾
你還好嗎？
Yeah.
Dale, he doesn't look too good.
還好
戴爾，他看上去不太好。
- I need to take him down.
- Yeah.
- 我需要送他下去。
- 是的
You can't get Scott on the radio?
你用無線電聯繫不到斯科特？
No.
No, I think he's-he's up ahead.
不
不，我認為他-他應該在前面吧。
Best not to stay too long at the Summit.
估計很快就要到峰頂了吧。
It's a long way to go, man.
我們還有很長一段路呢兄弟。
Head down,
one step at a time.
低下頭，一步一步走。
You got it, boss.
知道了，老闆。
You seen Dale?
你看到戴爾嗎？
Yeah, and he wasn』t looking too good, but...
有，他看上去不太好，不過····
Neal seem to have handle the situation.
尼爾應該搞的定這種情況。
Try to use your radio.
嘗試用無線電聯繫你。
- You kidding me.
- No.
- 你跟我開玩笑吧。
- 沒有
Guess it's not working, huh.
估計用不了，哈哈。
I'm going down to Camp 1.
我準備回到1號營地。
If he's not doing so well,I'm going to take him down to Base Camp.
如果他還是沒有好轉，我會送他回大本營的。
and I'll head back up.
然後我再上來
- You guys alright?
- Yeah.
- 你的夥計們都還好？
- 是的
He can't be too far ahead of you, mate.
他不會離你太遠的，夥計。
Yeah.
I'll make it down in half the time.
是的。我會盡快趕上的。
I'm going to catch him.
Woo.
我去找他。
喔。
Cheers, mate.
乾杯夥計們。
CAMP TWO : 21,300 ft
6,492 metres
2號營地：21300英尺 6492米
Rob to Guy.
羅布呼叫蓋爾。
- Rob to Guy. You up there, mate?
(MOUNT PUMORI, 5 MILES WEST OF EVEREST)
- 羅布呼叫蓋爾。夥計你在嗎？
（普摩力山，珠峰西側5公里）
- Guy to Rob. I'm here.
(MOUNT PUMORI, 5 MILES WEST OF EVEREST)
-蓋爾呼叫羅布，我在。
（普摩力山，珠峰西側5公里）
Good to hear you, Guy.
Where are you?
聽到你的聲音真好，蓋爾。
你在哪？
Camp 1, Pumori.
1號營地，普摩力
Yeah.
好的
There you go,
看到你了
Listen, I think you're on the wrong mountain there.
聽著，我覺得你應該走錯路了。
Look, I can't talk and we got to get out of here.
好的，不多說了我們準備離開這堙C
Alright, mate. Oh, listen.
You take care on the kiddy slope.
好的夥計。噢，聽著。你要注意小斜坡。
I ought to get back to the real thing.
我應該關注回該做的事上了。
Hey, don't worry, Rob.
I'll keep an eye on you.
嘿，別擔心，羅布
我會照看著你的。
Aye!
Watch out!
小心！
Aw!
ROB!
羅布！
- Rob!
- I got you.
- 羅布！
- 抓住你了！
Harold, you okay?
哈羅德，你沒事吧？
Is everyone okay?
大家都沒事吧？
We're okay!
我們沒事！
Come here, come here, come here.
Sit. Sit down, sit.
過來，過來，過來
坐。坐下。坐
I'm fine.
我沒事
Look at me.
看著我
- Look at me!
- I'm fine, mate.
- 看著我！
- 我沒事，夥計。
Look at me, Harold.
看著我，哈羅德。
Look.
I'm tell you, I'm alright.
嘿，我真的沒事。
- Okay.
- I'm alright.
- 好的
- 我沒事。
- Harold.
- Thank you.
- 哈羅德
- 謝謝
Don't do that to me again, aye.
別再這樣了好吧
Rob, I'm sorry.
羅布，抱歉。
Okay, mate.
好的夥計
I'll get drop back with Frank,he's struggling, alright?
我要過去看下弗蘭克，他正在奮力過來，好嗎？
- Alright.
- Okay.
- 好的
- Alright. Straight here.
(CAMP THREE : 24,000 ft  : 7,315 m)
- 好的，呆在這
（3號營地：24000英尺 7315米）
Let's get him on the oxygen.
給他吸點氧氣
Bravo to Scott Fischer.
呼叫斯科特
Mountain Madness, how do you copy?
瘋狂登山者，你收到嗎？
Hey, man.
Scott here.
嘿兄弟
我是斯科特
I've been down to Base Camp and I'm back to Camp 1.
我已經回過大本營，現在在1號營地。
I'm catch you tomorrow.
明天我會趕上你的。
What? You not going to rest up a day first, huh?
什麼？你不去休整下？
Scott, you sound a little rough.
Hey, take an extra day.
斯科特，這樣做不太好吧。
嘿，別那麼趕吧。
No way, Jose.
What, miss out on all the fun.
不行，這樣會錯過很多樂趣的。
It's a lot of up and down in...
one day even for you, Scott.
今天對你來說也是夠折騰的斯科特。
You know what they say, man.
你知道有句話叫
It's not the altitude,it's the attitude.
有志者事竟成
You sure you're going to be okay?
你確定你能挺得住？
- Scott?
- I'll be good.
- 斯科特？
- 我會搞定的
Just taking a shot of dexamethasone now.
我現在打針地塞米松。
Just don't push yourself too hard.
只是別逼自己太辛苦。
Okay?
Over and out.
好嗎？
結束通話
Rob, I've just been over the Miles to get a weather update.
羅布，我這邊剛收到新的天氣信息。
It's moving fast.
It's changed course slightly
有強風吹來，它的風向轉變了。
and it could still go north but
if it doesn't
它有可能還會像北吹但如果它轉變了
It's gonna hit sometime
on the 11th, I reckon.
我估計就有可能在11號跟你們碰上。
Get some weather forecast, Helen.
海倫，收集些天氣預報。
The mountain makes it's own weather.
山間天氣隨時在變
We're keeping an eye on it.
我們會多注意的
Yeah, sure.
Just, letting you know.
恩好的。只是把最新情況告訴你。
Appreciate it, Helen.
非常感謝，海倫
Why we do this to ourselves?
為什麼我們這樣對自己？
Oh, this is crazy.
噢，真是瘋狂。
You know I never told Krakauer this.
你知道嗎？我重來沒把這告訴克拉考爾
When he was asking us why we climb Everest.
當他問我們為什麼要登珠峰的時候。
When I'm at home...
當我在家···
I just got this big...
我感覺
black cloud following me.
諸事不順
You know, like a depression.
就很抑鬱
When I'm out here...
當我在外面···
on a mountain,any mountain,
爬山的時候，任何一座山
it's just like it's a cure.
我覺得什麼都好了
Feel like I'm reborn.
感覺重生一樣。
So, you're happy now?
那你現在應該挺開心的？
Now I'm starting to wonder.
現在我開始想
This is suffering, man.
這有點招罪，兄弟。
This is suffering.
確實有點招罪
Yeah.
是的
Suffer a few more days.
得忍受幾天。
The rest of your life, you'll be the guy that climb to the top of Everest.
在接下來的日子，你就是那個登上世界之巔的人了。
I just hope I get there.
我希望我能成功
Yeah.
是的
Just hope I get there and get home.
希望能順利登頂然後回家
What do you think, Mike?
你覺得怎樣，麥克？
Almost pretty good.
A little bit of wind up high.
還是挺好的。
風有些大。
I mean, if it picks up, we can
always come back down.
我覺得，如果風再大，我們還是可以下來的。
- Exactly.
- It's your call, Rob.
- 確實是
- 按你說的做，羅布
Let's get them all going.
讓我們出發吧
CAMP FOUR : 26,085 ft
7,951 m
4號營地：26085英尺 7951米
Hey, Rob!
嘿，羅布！
- You, okay?
- Not good!
- 你，還好？
- 不太好！
I'm hoping it's going to die down after sun down.
我希望太陽下山之後風應該會小點。
Been doing that.
應該會吧
I don't like this.
我討厭這天氣
We don't go if it doesn't calm.
我們等風小點再出發
- I talk to Scott when he come's here.
- Okay.
- 等斯科特過來了我再跟他談談。
- 好的
Scott!
斯科特！
- Scott!
- Anatoli, here.
- 斯科特！
- 阿納托利，這
Anatoli, where is Rob?
阿納托利，羅布在哪？
Where are they?
Did he go down?
他們在哪？
他下去了嗎？
Where's Rob?
What's Rob's team doing?
羅布在哪？
羅布的隊伍怎樣？
Rob will see if it passes.
羅布會知道的如果風過了
If he wait.
如果他想再等等
- We wait.
- Okay.
- 我們就等等
- 好的
Friday 10th May
五月10日 星期五
00:30 AM
凌晨 00：30
Hey, guys.
嘿 各位。
Come out and take a look.
出來看看
At least somebody up there loves us.
上天還是眷顧我們的
Nothing.
哪有
Where the storm go?
強風過境了？
Exactly.
沒錯
- That's crazy.
- You ready to saddle up?
- 真瘋狂
- 你準備出發了？
Okay, everyone.
好的，各位
We got a window.
我們有一個空窗期
We don't know how long it's going to last.
我們不知道會有多久
But we're going to go for it.
但我們需要把握這次機會
Be ready in half an hour.
半小時內收拾好
We have a 2 PM turn around.
Let's climb this thing.
來讓我們繼續登吧
Okay.
好的
So, today's the day, huh?
所以，今天就是幸運日咯？
Yeah.
是的
Now or never.
機不可失
Oh boy.
噢 夥計
The south Africans were laid out at Camp 3.
南非團隊已經困在3號營地了
They never made it into Camp 4.
他們很難再上4號營地了
Probably got caught up in it.
很可能遇上強風
- Maybe it blew though early.
- Yeah. Well, it hit us all night.
- 也許這風掛得比較傲早
- 是的，好吧，它刮了我們一晚上。
But that was nothing,absolutely nothing.
但不是還好好地，完全沒事。
So, it's definitely worth a shot.
所以這完全是個好事
I'll radio Ed,tell him you're continuing.
我用無線電聯繫 Ed，告訴他你繼續向前
Any messages?
還有什麼消息嗎？
Yeah. Ring Jan, tell her that we're heading out.
有，告訴簡我們已經擺脫困境了。
I'll call you, Helen, in 12 hours
when we get to the Summit.
12小時後我們登頂了我會再打給你的海倫
Turn around is 2 PM.
Good luck and
god speed to you all.
祝好運，上天保佑你們。
Okay. Thanks, Helen.
Bye bye.
好的，謝謝海倫。
再見
I'll see you guys up there.
我會在上面與你們相遇的
- Take it easy, Scott.
- Let's do it.
- 放輕鬆，斯科特
- 出發吧
I get a couple of hours of sleep and I'll be right behind you.
我先睡會兒，我就在你們後面。
- Yeah, okay.
- See you at the top.
- 恩，好的
- 峰頂見
- Have fun, Pittman. Yeah.
- You get some rest, okay.
- 旅途愉快 皮特曼
- 你先休息下吧
See you there.
峰頂見
- You got the ropes for the Hillary Step?
- Yeah.
- 你有準備繩子到希拉堮|嗎？
- 有
- Okay.
- 好的
Okay.
好
THE BALCONY : 27,600 ft 8,412 m
THE BALCONY ：27600英尺 8412米
04:30 AM
凌晨04：30
Can we go any faster?
我們能再走快點嗎？
Not a chance we can go faster here.
在這奡N只能走這麼了
It's too difficult.
This could take a while.
這很困難的，需要些時間。
We're losing time.
我們在浪費時間
Beck, what's wrong?
貝克，怎麼了？
I don't know.
我不知道。
I had a operation couple of years ago on my eyes.
我的雙眼在幾年前做了手術
That might be it.
有些不舒服
I don't know.
我不知道
Okay.
Guys, go in front of us.
好的
夥計們，走我們前面
- Alright, Beck, let's sit you down.
- Okay.
-好的 貝克，先坐下來
-好的
Beck.
Look at me.
貝克
看著我
I need to send you down with someone.
我需要把你和別人送下去
- No. I don't want to go down, Rob.
- No, you got to go down.
- 不，我不想下去，羅布
- 不，你必須下去
I don't want to go down.
我不想下去
Okay.
那行
Alright, Beck.Listen.
好的，貝克，聽著
You can wait here for half and hour.
Beck, listen to me.
你可以在這媯奶@時半會
貝克 聽我說
If it gets better by then,
join in the queue and keep going up.
如果感覺好點，在跟上隊伍。
If it doesn't get better, Beck,
如果不見好轉，貝克
- I'm sorry, mate. It's over.
- Okay.
- 我很抱歉，夥計。你必須放棄。
- 好的
Sherpas are going to go and drop off the extra oxygen on the south side while they can.
可以的話夏爾巴人將會在前方放下額外的氧氣供給在南側
I'm going to send one of them down for you. Is that clear?
我去拿一瓶給你，清楚了嗎？
- Yeah?
- Alright.
- 清楚嗎？
- 好的
Okay, mate.
Alright.
行，夥計。
好的
God speed.
上天保佑
Sandy, do you want to go down?
桑迪，你想下去嗎？
What?
No, no way.
什麼？
不，不想
Look, Lopsang, I'm going to make it to the top.
Lopsang聽著，我一定要登頂。
- Do you understand?
- Okay.
- 你明白了嗎？
- 好的
- I'm not going back, okay?
- Okay.
- 我不會回去的，好嗎？
- 好的
THE SOUTH EAST RIDGE
東南山脊
Hey, where are the ropes?
嘿，繩子在哪？
There is no rope.
No rope.
這堥S有繩子。
沒有繩子
Yeah?
They should have been fixed.
怎麼了？
繩子應該是被固定在這的
Do you have more in your pack.
在你包你還有繩子嗎？
Lopsang has the ropes. He's not here.
Lopsang 有繩子，但他不在這。
- Harold, no ropes?
- No.
- 哈羅德，沒繩子？
- 沒有
- Harold.
- Neal.
- 哈羅德
- 尼爾
Hey, Rob.
嘿 羅布
Listen, we got a problem here, mate.
聽著兄弟，我們在這有個問題
There's no fixed ropes on the crevasse to Hillary Step, over.
在希拉堮|沒有繩子固定在冰川壁。
Where is Ang Dorjee and Lopsang?
昂多吉和Lopsang 在哪？
Yeah, I got Ang Dorjee here but there's not sign of Lopsang.
昂多吉在這但Lopsang不在這。
So, me, Neal, Anatoli are going to set some new ones, over.
那，我、尼爾和阿納托利在這重新設置新的。
- Fine then.
- Yeah.
- 好的
- 行
- Good.
- Let's do it.
- 好的
- 來吧
- What's going on?
- No fixed rope.
- 怎麼了？
- 沒有固定繩
What?
什麼？
That's it.
就是這樣
1 step at a time, Doug.
一步一步走，道格拉斯
Come on, Dougy.
Deep breaths, Dougy.
加油，道格拉斯
深呼吸，道格拉斯
Come on, mate.
Keep it on. Keep it on.
加油，夥計們。
堅持，堅持！
- Rob.
- Deep breaths, Dougy. Hang on.
- 羅布
- 深呼吸，道格拉斯，堅持住。
Hang on.
堅持住
You can do this , Dougy.
你可以的，道格拉斯。
- I know you can, pal.
- Yeah?
- 我知道你可以的兄弟。
- 恩？
I don't want to see you back here a third time, mate.
我不想第三次還在這見你夥計。
John.
You heading back down?
喬恩
你要往回走？
There's a hold up.
這有些耽擱
There's no fixed ropes above the South Summit.
峰頂南側沒有固定繩在上面
Yeah.
I know, mate.
好的
我知道了夥計
But we are sorting that situation out now.
但我們已經處理了現在
Ran out of juice waiting.
氧氣快用完了。
Go.
I'm sorry, Rob.
走吧，
我很抱歉羅布。
That's your call, pal.
只能幫你到這了兄弟
I don't want to run out of oxygen up there.
我不想走到上面的時候氧氣用完了。
Sorry, Rob.
抱歉 羅布
We've a little bit of a set back.
我們遇上了些麻煩。
Lou, Stuart and John Taske
just turned back, just...
路易、斯圖亞特和喬恩他們返回去了
just below the South Summit.
回到了珠峰南側下面
- How are the conditions so far?
- Cold and windy.
- 上面的情況怎樣？
- 非常冷且大風
- Okay, let me know, Rob.
- Okay, Helen. Thanks, bye bye.
- 好的，有什麼事就通知我，羅布
- 好的，海倫。謝謝，拜拜。
I hope we're not looking at another year
我不希望我們要等下次
with no clients at the top.
下次就沒有客戶可以登上了
Well, if that ain't going to
move them pretty soon.
好吧，如果他們還不走快點
They're out of time, aren't they?
他們真的就沒時間了吧？
Yeah.
And...
是的
而且···
What's Jon going to say about that in his article.
不知道喬恩會在他的文章堶惚蝏羃
- It's Rob.
(THE HILLARY STEP : 28,740 ft  : 8,760 m)
- 我是羅布
（希拉堮|：28740英尺 8760米）
- Guy.
(THE HILLARY STEP : 28,740 ft  : 8,760 m)
- 各位
（希拉堮|：28740英尺 8760米）
- We just lost Lou, Stuart and John Taske.
(The Hillary Step : 8,760 metres)
- 路易斯、斯圖亞特和喬恩離開了
（希拉堮|：28740英尺 8760米）
What's going on?
What's the hold up?
怎麼回事？
什麼事情耽擱了？
Yeah, yeah, mate.
We...
是的，是的兄弟們
我····
We sent Anatoli and Neal to the top of the Step
我派阿納托利和尼爾去「面梯」
fixing the ropes.
固定住繩子
We're at the-
at the Face's Step, over.
我們正在··正在「面梯」
Rob, Mike.
羅布，麥克
- How's Doug doing?
- Doug's just behind me.
- 道格拉斯怎麼了？
- 道格拉斯剛還在我身邊
I left him behind to scoot forward.
我為了趕上來把他拋在後面了
Yeah, I got eyes on you right now.
Yep, that's me.
好吧，我看到你了
是的，是我
Let's move this
來把它解決掉吧
as quickly as possible, over.
盡快吧。
We'll start moving everybody up
as soon as we get the all clear.
一旦搞定了大家就再出發。
Rob to base. Rob to base, Hel.
Copy, Helen.
羅布呼叫大本營 羅布呼叫大本營 海倫
收到我是海倫
- You alright?
- Copy. Base camp to Rob.
- 你還好？
- 收到，大本營呼叫羅布
Have you... Have you
heard from Scott?
斯科特有···有會叫你們嗎？
Anyone manage to find out where he is, over.
有沒有人能找到他在哪。
Woo-Eee!
Yo, dude.
喔~~哇~
好吧兄弟
Look. Where are you, mate? We got a
real logjam here at the Hillary Step, over.
聽著，你現在在哪，兄弟？我們這堹u的成僵局了在希拉堮|。
- I'm more than an hour behind.
- Just chill.
- 我比你們晚超過一個小時。
- 放鬆點。
People just sitting there using up their oxygen.
大家坐在這正在耗費著氧氣呢。
Get here as soon as you can.
盡快上來吧
- Oh my god. You okay, Beck?
- Yeah.
- 我的天啊。貝克你沒事吧？
- 我沒事
Oh I got a little problem with my eyes.
You guys turning back?
噢，我的眼睛出了點問題。
你的夥伴都返回了？
There's a logjam below
the Hillary Step.
在希拉堮|上面出現了些問題僵持住了。
It's crazy.
Come down with us.
很難搞定
跟我們一起返回吧！
No, I can't.
Promise Rob I'd wait for him.
不，不行。我答應了羅布在這等他回來
- Your call.
- I'm good.
- 那你看著辦吧。
- 我沒事
See you down there.
回去再見
Neal.
Andy.
尼爾
安迪
Okay, Anatoli.
好的，阿納托利
I'm done.
我搞定了。
All through.
Safe to climb.
可以通行了，攀登沒問題。
Okay, we're climbing up!
好的，我們現在爬過來！
- Hey, Mike.
- What?
- 嘿，麥克。
- 怎麼了？
- You mind if I go first?
- Why.
- 不介意的話我想先走一步？
- 為什麼
I'm running pretty low on "O".
我的氧氣不太多了
Rob, it's Mike here.
羅布，我是麥克
Eh. We have the all clear on this end.
恩，道路暢通無阻了
I'm going to stay here with Yasuko till we got a clear line.
我會在這陪著恭子知道她好點
I'll be here till I get a visual on Doug. Over and out
我也會在這陪著道格拉斯直到他好點，通話結束。
* 01:14 PM *
*下午1點14*
We did it.
我們成功了！
We did it!
Thank you very much.
非常感謝。
Thank you, Mom.
謝謝你，母親。
* 02:00 PM *
*下午2點整*
Yasuko.
Yasuko
- Seven.
- 7
- 7 summits.
- 登頂第七峰
Come here.
真的
I'm so proud of you, Yasuko.So proud.
我真的很為你感到驕傲，Yasuko，真替你感到驕傲。
Thank you.
謝謝
Rob to base.
羅布呼叫大本營
Rob, this is Helen.
Hello, where are you?
羅布，我是海倫。
你好，你到哪了？
I'm at the top of Everest, Helen.
We made it.
我們在珠峰之巔，海倫。
我們成功了。
- Yeah.
- They did it.
- 是嘛！
- 他們成功了。
Copy us, over.
收到嗎？
Oh, we copy you loud and clear, Rob.
好的，我們收到了！非常清晰地收到了，羅布。
It's wonderful to hear your voice up there.
聽到你們成功登頂真的太好了！
Who are you with again, Beck?
還有誰成功登頂了嗎？貝克呢？
At the moment I'm with Mike and Yasuko.
現在有麥克、Yasuko和我
Good job, man.
真棒，兄弟
Rob, see you.
Thank you.
羅布，再見。
謝謝
Jon and Kasischke have already been and gone.
喬恩和Kasischke上來了很快就下去了。
Doug is just coming over the horizon.
道格拉斯正在上來但還沒見到。
And-And what about Beck?
那··那貝克呢？
Beck was having a problem with his eye sight.
貝克的眼部視力出了點問題。
He waited on the Southeast Ridge,on the Balcony.
他在東南山脊那等著。
For the first people who came back, over.
第一批人員已經回去了
And I... I guess you'll be leaving right away, yes?
我··我估計你也應該快下來了是嗎？
Moving off in a few minutes just as soon I see Doug,
我再等會，等道格拉斯上來
we'll be heading back down, over.
然後我們就下去
Alright, understood.
Oh, that's terrific, Rob.
好的，明白了。
羅布，你真了不起。
We're all keeping our fingers cross for Doug.
我們都會為道格拉斯加油的
Over and out, Helen.
結束通話，海倫
- Congratulation.
- You're welcome.
- 恭喜
- 不客氣
Yeah, ladsy.
You did it.
好的，ladsy
你成功了
Woo yee!
You look terrible.
你看上去不太好
My stories,not so good, man.
自食其力是這樣的，兄弟
- You see Doug?
- Oh, yeah. He's way way...
- 你看到道格拉斯了嗎？
- 噢，是的。他在後··後··
way back there, man.
後面，兄弟
Hey, Roberto.
Where're the rest of your guys.
嘿，羅伯托
你的其他隊員呢？
'Cause I'm pretty sure my whole team
我敢保證我的全部隊員
made it up, yeah.
都成功登頂了，不是嘛
Heh heh heh.
I saw them.
哈 哈 哈
我看見他們的
Don't worry.
I won't tell Krakauer.
別擔心
我不會告訴克拉考爾的。
Hold on, mate.
I know it's bad, huh.
別著急，夥計
我知道沒你好，哈。
I'll have to give you this year.
這次就先讓你風光下吧。
Scott, you really don't look too good.
斯科特，你真的看上去不太好
- Lopsang.
- Yeah.
- Lopsang
- 是的
Come, mate.
Let's get him down.
來夥計，把他送下去。
Alright.
好的。
Let's go.
走吧。
Harold.
What're you doing?
哈羅德
你在幹嘛呢？
I'm just trying to sort out the "O".
我在試下還有沒有氧氣。
I can't find any full ones.
我找不到一瓶是滿的
There's full bottles, I saw them on the way up.
我看到在路上有些氧氣瓶是滿的。
No.
沒有
So I pretty sure you should have another look.
我肯定你應該在看看其他的
- No. They just have, they're not full.
- Harold. Listen, I saw...
- 沒，沒有滿的
- 哈羅德，聽著，我看····
Look, Mike.
I've checked twice, alright.
聽著，麥克
我都檢查了兩次了，好嘛。
Yeah.
Alright, man.
好的
好吧，兄弟。
I'm going down.
我回去了
Harold.
哈羅德
03:15 PM
下午3點15分
Doug. Doug.
Doug.
道格拉斯·道格拉斯
道格拉斯
- It's over, mate.
- No.
- 不行了，兄弟
- 不
I' sorry.
No no no no.
我很抱歉
不 不 不
Doug.
You're too late, okay.
道格拉斯
你太慢了，好吧。
You guys keep going, mate,
I'll catch up.
夥計們，你們先走，我會趕上你們。
Doug. Doug.
Doug, listen to me.
道格拉斯·道格拉斯
道格拉斯，聽我說。
- It's way too long, it's over.
- No, it's not.
- 還有好長路呢，不行的。
- 不，一定可以
Now, listen to me, mate.
I'm sorry.
夥計，現在聽我的
我很抱歉
But I got to turn you around.
但我必須把你送回去。
Okay.
好嗎？
I can do it.
我可以的
It's right here, man.It's right here.
就快到了兄弟，就快到了。
I'm not coming back next year, man.
It's my last chance.
兄弟，我下年不會再來了，這是我最後的機會。
You got to let me do this.
你必須讓我繼續。
Let me do this.
讓我繼續。
- Okay.
- Please, Rob.
- 好的
- 求你了，羅布
- Let's do it. Let's get it done.
- Alright.
- 走，去完成登頂。
- 好的
- Come on.
- Thanks, man.
- 來吧
- 兄弟，謝謝
Alright, Doug.
好的，道格拉斯
And there's no hope,
I get it.
沒希望了
我知道
My double wide trailer.
我的雙寬拖車
- Beck?
- What?
- 貝克？
- 怎麼了？
- Are you okay?
- Who is there?
- 你還好嗎？
- 你是？
- It's Jon.
- I'm not seeing too well, Jon.
- 我是喬恩
- 我看得不太清楚，喬恩。
I'm freezing.
我快凍死了。
Mike's just behind me.
麥克在我身後
He's back there with Yasuko.
他跟Yasuko一起回去
You'll be okay.
Mike's right behind me.
你會沒事的。麥克就在我身後
You okay?
你可以嗎？
I'll see you then.
回去見
04:00 PM
下午4點整
- There she is.
(04:00 PM)
- 到頂了
（下午4點整）
Almost there, mate.
就到了，夥計
Dig deep, Doug.
Dig deep.
深呼吸，道格拉斯
深呼吸
There you go.
做得好
Yehhhh!
Huh, you made it.
哈，你成功了
You did it.
Huh.
你成功了
哈
Yeah.Because of you, man.
是的，因為有你的幫助，兄弟。
Guy to Rob.
You read me, mate?
蓋爾呼叫羅布
兄弟聽到嗎？
Guy to Rob.
Are you there?
蓋爾會叫羅布
你在嗎？
This going to the kids.
來見證了孩子們。
Yehhh!
Hang in there, Doug.
穩住，道格拉斯
Come on.
來
Easy.
Here, I got it.
慢慢來
來，好了
Yeah.
I'm okay.
好的
我沒事
Yeah, I got it.
好的，我沒事
- Come on, let's get you up.
- I need...
- 來，讓我送你回去
- 我需要····
- Huh?
- Need more "O".
- 恩？
- 需要更多氧氣
No, Doug.
We can't give you more "O".
不，道格拉斯
這堥S有更多氧氣了
We got to get down to the South Summit, come on.
我們需要回到山峰南側，來吧。
Guy calling to Everest Base Camp.
Are you there, Helen?
蓋爾呼叫珠峰大本營
海倫，在嗎？
Guy, this is Helen.
How is it going?
蓋爾，我是海倫
你還好嗎？
Yeah, I'm fine.
恩，我很好。
I got a clear view of the Summit and...
我這堹鈰鰷M楚看到峰頂，然後····
you know, we still got climbers up there.
They are not any of ours, right?
你知道嗎，我們仍有登山隊員在上面呢。
他們不是我們的隊員，是嗎？
We got 3 up and they're all on their way down.
我們有3名隊員上去了並且應該原途返回了
Well. What are they doing there so late?
好的，那為什麼他們那麼晚離開？
And there's 2 o'clock turn around time,they're way past it.
他們不是應該在下午兩點起離開嗎，他們已經錯過了。
Here we go. Cloud coming out of the valley. It's a lot of it.
已經有云層從山谷那吹過去了，很厚的雲層。
Thanks.
I'm calling them now, Guy.
好的
蓋爾，我現在聯繫他們。
Rob, come in.
This is Helen.
羅布 聽到嗎？
我是海倫
Rob, come in.
This is Helen.
羅布 聽到嗎？
我是海倫
Whoa!
哇！
Easy. Easy. Easy, Dougy.
There you go. There you go.
小心·小心·小心道格拉斯
慢慢來，慢慢來。
We're going to go around the corner.
我們要轉過這個角落
That's it.
好的
Rob, is that you?
羅布，是你嗎？
Beck?
貝克？
It's Mike, mate.
我是麥克，夥計。
- What're you doing here?
- I can't see, it's bad.
- 你在這幹嘛？
- 我看不見，太糟糕了
You guys alright?
你們還好嗎？
We got a problem with Beck.
貝克有點麻煩。
Hey, Mike.
We're getting low on "O".
嘿，麥克
我們的氧氣不足了
We got to move.
我們要趕快走
I'll get you to stand up, okay.
我扶你起來，好嗎？
- I'll take Yasuko.
- That's it.
- 我帶著Yasuko
- 好的
I got you.
扶住你了
You're okay.
你還行嗎？
Doug, come on.
Come on.
道格拉斯，堅持
堅持
I'm cold.
我很冷
Oxygen level : 0
氧氣水平：0
Mike, Harold, Ang Dorjee,
麥克，哈羅德，昂多吉
put the brakes on, guys.
We got a problem.
大夥兒等等
我們這有些問題。
- We're out of gas, Doug.
- Alright.
- 我們沒氧氣，道格拉斯
- 好嗎
We're out of gas. We need to keep moving, come on.
我們沒氧氣，我們需要繼續走回去，來吧
Come on.
來吧
Mike, Harold, do you copy?
I need someone...
麥克、哈羅德，你們收到嗎？
我需要人···
I need someone to come
back up with oxygen, over.
我需要人帶點氧氣上來。
Somebody, please.
I'm begging you.
有人嗎，謝謝
我求你了
Doug, come on, mate.
Come on!
道格拉斯，來吧，夥計
來吧！
Harold, do you copy, over.
哈羅德，你收到嗎？
Has anyone got eyes on Ang Dorjee?
有人看到過昂多吉嗎？
Mate, I have just had Ang Dorjee go past me heading down, over.
夥計，昂多吉走在我的前面
He's going down.
他下去了
Can you stop him?
Can you turn him around?
你能讓他停停嗎？
能讓他回來嗎？
I need someone to come back up now.
現在我需要有人來幫下我
Hey!
Ang Dorjee.
嘿！
昂多吉
Ang Dorjee!
昂多吉！
Base camp, do you copy, over.
大本營，收到嗎？
Helen to Rob.
Go ahead.
海倫呼叫羅布
請說
Helen, please.
海倫
I need a bottle of gas at the top of the Hillary Step.
我需要一瓶氧氣在希拉堮|高處
I can't get him down without it.
沒有氧氣我無法把道格拉斯送下來
I'm really stuck.
我在堅持著
Understood.
清楚了
That you need a bottle of oxygen at the bottom of the Hillary Step.
你需要一瓶氧氣在希拉堮|高處
We're sending it up to you as soon as we can.
我們盡快把氧氣瓶送上去給你
At the top.
在高處
The last thing I said to Ang Dorjee was please
最後一件告訴昂多吉的事是請他
bring 2 bottles of gas at the South Summit.
帶兩瓶氧氣到山峰南側
Yes, uh.
Copy that, Rob.
好的
收到了，羅布
Boys. There's oxygen at the South Summit, right?
夥計們，在山峰南側那有氧氣瓶，是嗎？
No, Rob!
This is Harold.
沒有，羅布！
我是哈羅德
There's no oxygen at South Summit.
山峰南側沒有氧氣瓶
Repeat.
No "O".
重複
沒有氧氣
Ang Dorjee stashed 4 bottles there, Harold.
昂多吉放了4瓶氧氣在那，哈羅德
Harold, where are you?
哈羅德，你在哪？
Can you hear me, Harold?
聽到嗎，哈羅德？
Harold.
哈羅德
Harold, can you hear me?
哈羅德，你聽到嗎？
Figure it'll take me about
我估計要花
half an hour to get back up
to the South Summit.
半小時才能到達山峰南側
Okay.
好的
I'm coming.
我現在來
If you don't have oxygen, mate,
夥計，如果你沒有足夠氧氣
don't come up, don't come up.
We're moving on.
就別上來了，別上來。
我們繼續前進
I'm coming up to you, Rob.
我現在過去你那，羅布。
Doug, come on, mate.
Come on!
道格拉斯，堅持，夥計
堅持！
Rob, this is Base Camp.
羅布，這堿O大本營
I copy you, Carol.
我收到，卡羅爾
Rob, can you get yourself down?
羅布，你自己能夠下來嗎？
Carol, we're not at that point yet.
卡羅爾，我們還下不來
Rob, can you let us know who you're with?
羅布，你能告訴我你跟誰在一起嗎？
I'm with Doug.
我和道格拉斯在一起
We're both listening.
我們都聽到
Come on, Dougy. Come on, mate.
One more alping, come on.
來吧，道格拉斯，來吧，兄弟
再堅持下，來吧
Rob, what is Doug's state of consciousness?
羅布，道格拉斯的意識狀態怎樣？
He's really weak.
他意識很弱
He collapsed after he ran out of oxygen.
他的氧氣一用完了就不行了
Okay.
Give him 8 mg of dexamethasone.
好的
給他8毫克地塞米松
That's 2 tablets, Rob.
兩片，羅布
Guy to Rob.
蓋爾呼叫羅布
Go ahead Guy.
I got you, mate.
說吧蓋爾
我看到你了，夥計
Rob, I suggest you get yourself down.
羅布，我建議你一個人離開那。
You know you're doing no good up there.
你清楚這樣繼續下去是不行的。
And we got people we can send up there to help Doug,
我們可以再找些人上來幫助道格拉斯
but you got to get yourself down, you understand?
但你必須先下來，明白嗎？
I mean, come on, mate.
We're playing with a man's life here.
你知道的夥計，道格拉斯的命運在我手堙C
There's no way
I'm leaving Doug behind.
我不能放棄他
我不能把道格拉斯留在這
We got to keep moving, mate.
我們需要繼續前進，夥計
We got to keep moving,we are in some trouble.
我們需要離開這，在這媟|很麻煩。
Yeah, Helen gonna... need some help.
So I'm gonna try make my way back.
好的，海倫需要···需要些幫助。
所以我需要上去
- Okay?
- Okay.
- 好嗎？
- 好
Alright.
Go on.
好的
繼續
Hey, Scott.
Scott.
嘿，斯科特
斯科特
You okay?
你還好？
Lopsang.
I'm done, pal.
我不行了，夥計
I'm done.
我不行了
You go,send Anatoli.
你去，給阿納托利
Send Anatoli back with some "O".
去給阿納托利送些氧氣
- Okay.
- Go.
- 好的
- 去吧
Okay.
好的
I will send back, Anatoli.
給阿納托利送完我就會回來
- Let's go.
- You go down.
- 去吧
- 你下去
No, mate.
不，夥計
No. I'm not leaving you behind, Doug.
不，我不會讓你留在這的，道格拉斯
- Come on.
- Got to rest.
- 來吧
- 我需要休息下
No, Doug! Come on!
Come on with me!
不行，道格拉斯！堅持住！
一起加油！
I need 10 good minutes, Doug.
Come on.
道格拉斯，再走10分鐘。
來吧
Please, let me go.
你就讓我呆這吧，求你了。
Damn it.
We're at the bottom of the Step.
該死的
我們在希拉堮|最下方了
Come on, this leg.
This leg, Dougy, come on.
來吧，這隻腳用力
這隻腳用力，道格拉斯，來吧
Come on.
來吧
Here we go.
好的
Oh no.
噢 不
Hey. Hold it down.
Hold that down.
嘿，把它穩住
把它穩住
Come on, come on.
Get the chairs.
來，來
拾起那把椅子
No, no, no.
Come on, Dougy!
不 不 不
堅持，道格拉斯！
Go, let's go!
Hurry up!
走，繼續！
快點！
Doug. I'm going to go to the South Summit to get oxygen.
道格拉斯，我要去山峰南側去拿氧氣
Okay.
Got to find oxygen.
好嗎？
我去找氧氣
But, you got to stay here!
但，你必須呆在這！
Okay, stay here!
Don't move, I'll be back!
好的，呆在這！
別走開，我會回來的！
Rob.
羅布
Hey, Rob.
嘿，羅布
Hey!
Stop!
嘿！
停！
That's the wrong way!
走錯路了！
Hey!
嘿！
Turn back!
回來！
Easy.
小心點
Hey, Rob!
嘿，羅布！
Rob!
羅布！
- I got...
- Harold?
- 我拿
- 哈羅德？
I got oxygen.
我拿到氧氣了
Here.
I found some half empty ones.
這
我找到些用了一半的
Where's Doug?
道格拉斯去哪了？
Doug's gone.
道格拉斯掉下去了
What?
什麼？
Gone.
死了
- Come on.
- Go!
- 來吧
- 走！
Come on!
加油！
Camp 4 is that way.
這邊去4號營地
Get up!
Let's go.
起來！
繼續走
Come on.
Beck.
來吧
貝克
I'll get help!
我去找人幫忙！
Neal!
尼爾！
- Anatoli.
- Where-Where are they?
- 阿納托利
- 他們··他們在哪？
They're still out there.
Jon!
I need help!
喬恩！
我需要幫助！
What?
什麼？
Get out there!
I need help!
離開這！
我需要幫助！
I can't.
I can't see, Anatoli.
我看
我看不見，阿納托利
I'm snow blind.
我雪盲了
Beck.
Doug.
貝克
道格拉斯。
They need help.
They're still out there.
他們需要幫助
他們還在那
I go find them.
You stay here.
我去找他們
你呆在這
12:00 AM
凌晨12點
Good job.
做到好
Hey!
嘿！
Anatoli!
阿納托利
Need "O".
需要氧氣
- Can you walk?
- I can't!
- 你還能走？
- 走不動了！
I'll come back!
我會回來的!
I'll stay!
我在這等！
Give me that, come on.
把那給我，來吧。
- It won't budge. It's frozen!
- Take this.
- 這用不了，它凍住了！
- 用這個
The gloves.
手套
I'm sorry.
對不起
Come on, mate.
來吧，夥計
Come on, Harold.
來吧，哈羅德
Thanks for coming back.
謝謝你來幫我
- Hello, Base Camp.
- Helen, it's Jan.
- 你好，大本營
- 海倫，我是簡
Why haven't I heard from you?
Why hasn't anybody call me?
為什麼我沒從你們那收到消息的？
為什麼你們每人給我打電話？
They've been hit by a storm, Jan.
It's really bad.
簡，他們遇到冰雪暴了
情況很危險
- Where is he?
- We don't know exactly. But...
- 羅布在哪？
- 我們不太知道他在哪，但是
He was still on the Summit at 4:00.
下午4點的時候他還在峰頂
Oh no.
Can he get down?
噢 不
他能下得來嗎？
Rob can,but Doug can't.
羅布可以的，但道格拉斯應該不行。
There's at least 13 people stranded up there and...
上面至少還有13人被困在上面與此同時··
while the storm is getting worse.
冰雪暴越來越厲害了
Helen!
海倫！
Get Ang Dorjee up there.
He'll bring them down.
讓昂多吉上來。
他會把他們送下去的
- Helen, do you understand?
- Helen. Give me an update.
- 海倫，你明白了嗎？
- 海倫，跟我說下最新情況
Get Ang Dorjee up there.
讓昂多吉上去
Jan, yep.
We will get him.
簡，是
我們會把他送下來的
And I will call you
the minute I hear from him.
已找到他我會馬上通知你的
- As soon as I hear from him.
- Thanks, Helen.
- 只要已找到他
- 謝謝你，海倫
- Alright.
- Okay.
- 好的
- 好
- Where is he?
- Guy, I haven't heard from him.
- 他在哪？
- 蓋爾，我沒找到他
- Okay, I'll get him.
- I've been trying.
- 好吧，我去找他
- 我一直在試著聯繫他
- Guy.
- Just hang on, hang on.
- 蓋爾
- 等等，等等
Rob, it's Guy.
Where are you?
羅布，我是蓋爾
你在哪？
Guy, I've been doing that for the last 2 hours.
蓋爾，2小時前我就在聯繫他了
Alright. Alright.
Rob, it's Guy.
好的，好的
羅布，我是蓋爾
- Just keep your energy, mate.
- Helen.
- 要保持體能啊，夥計。
- 海倫
Once you catch a break, you move.
You know the drill.
一找到機會，就繼續走
你知道怎麼做的
Hey, Guy. We got a stash of oxygen on the South Col.
嘿，蓋爾。我們在營地南面放了些氧氣瓶
- Whoever needs it can have it.
- That's the way, thank you.
- 你們要用就拿去吧
- 好的，謝謝
Faust's team are gonna go up, they got a man to search,
浮士德的團隊需要上去，需要有人上去找下
as soon as they can.
一有可能就去
Anyone who is going, we're going to leave at dawn with the commity.
任何上去的人，一定要在黎明前務必返回來
That's right, David.
就是這樣，大衛。
Go and let Ed knows what's going on, I'll be right behind you.
去讓Ed瞭解目前的情況，我等會跟上。
- Camp 4, come in.
- Okay, great.
- 4號營地，收到嗎？
- 行，好的
Hey, Rob.  Rob, can you hear me?
( 03:00 AM )
嘿，羅布。羅布，你能收到嗎？
（凌晨3點整）
David Breashears has a stash of oxygen at the South Col that we can use.
大衛有些氧氣瓶放在了營地南側，我們可以用。
Alright, mate. Well, we're all organizing a team, we're coming to get you.
好的，夥計。好的，我們現在組織了一支隊伍，我們正在上去救你。
Burning up.
好熱啊。
No.
不。
Yasuko.
Ohhh.
噢~~
Andy!
安迪！
Come on!
堅持住！
Rob, talk to me, please. Pick up.
( Saturday, 11th May )
羅布，請回答我，請回答我。
（星期六，5月11日）
- Pick up, mate. Please
( 05:00 AM )
- 夥計請回答我
（上午5點整）
Was there any word from the others?
有收到其他人的信息嗎？
Anatoli managed to get 3 climbers back from the South Col last night. But...
昨晚阿納托利設法帶3名登山隊員從南側下來，但是···
Beck and Yasuko are still out there.
貝克和恭子仍在上面
They're trying to mount a search
他們正嘗試設置搜尋
but everyone who's been up there is exhausted.
但在上面的每一個人都已經精疲力竭了
- Base.
- Rob, is that you?
- 大本營
- 羅布，是你嗎？
Rob, where are you?
We're sending people for you.
羅布，你在哪？
我們現在派人上去找你
Rob, this is Base Camp.
羅布，這堿O大本營
I can't.
我不能
Can't move anymore.
Can't move anymore
不能動了
Hey, mate. Yeah, I know.
I know, mate. I know.
嘿，夥計，是的，我知道
我知道，夥計，我知道
You got to keep on moving.
你必須動起來
Hands...
手····
I can't feel my hands, they're frozen.
我感覺不到我的手了，都被凍住了
There's "D" ice on the ice.
這堛熙楞靮p
I got "D" ice in my mask.
我的防護面具上面都是厚厚的雪
That's good. You got to get that mask working. You got to.
好吧，你需要讓你的防護面具運轉起來，你必須這樣做
The sun's going to come up and...
太陽快出來了
you know you can get warmer and you can get moving.
這樣你就可以暖和些然後就能繼續動起來了
- Guy.
- Yeah.
- 蓋爾
- 是的
Guy.
蓋爾
Harold was here.
Where did he go?
哈羅德在這的
他去哪了？
Rob.
Is Doug with you?
羅布
道格拉斯跟你在一起嗎？
Doug.
Doug's gone.
道格拉斯
道格拉斯去世了
Harold is gone.
哈羅德也去世了
I'm going to need a little help.
我需要些幫助
Okay.
Rob, you got to get yourself down.
好的
羅布，你需要返回來大本營
Where are you?
你在哪？
Guy.
蓋爾
I'm in the...in the little...
我在···在這小···
in the little dip just below the South Summit.
在這山峰南邊下面的小傾角那
Alright, you can do this.
好的，你可以堅持住的。
You just got to, you know, pull yourself out of that dip,
你懂的，你必須，必須讓自己離開那個小傾角
and slide the rest of the way.
從那條路上滑下來
Guy, send them boys.
蓋爾，派些人上去他們那
Okay. I'm going to need a little help.
好的，我需要點幫助
I got some Sheapas coming up there with tea and oxygen.
我和一些夏爾巴人帶些茶和氧氣一起上去那
You just got to come on down, mate.
你一定要下來，夥計
Aye, come on down.
好嗎，要下來
Rob.
羅布
Can you patch Jan through?
你能讓簡和他溝通嗎？
- To Rob?
- Pat-Patch her through.
- 和羅布？
- 讓他跟簡溝通下
Let's-Let's just try it.
Let's just...
來··來嘗試下
來嘗試下
put the satphone next to the radio
and uh.
將衛星電話放在無線電旁邊
If anyone can motivate him to move, and Jan will.
只有簡可以激勵他重新站起來
Guy to Rob.
蓋爾呼叫羅布
Can you read me?
你能收到嗎？
- Rob, are you there?
- We're getting him now.
- 羅布，你在嗎？
- 我們聯繫到他了
Rob, this is Helen.
羅布，我是海倫
Copy.
收到了
Rob, I got Jan for you.
羅布，我幫你聯繫到簡
My Jan?
我的妻子？
Yeah. She's just here.
是的，她在這
- Jan, you're on.
- Okay.
- 簡，你可以說了
- 好的
Hi, sweetheart.
How are you doing?
寶貝
你還好嗎？
Hi, my love.
我的愛人
I'm a bit
我有點
a bit cold.
有點冷
My love, I'm okay.
我的愛人，我還好
I know you are.
我知道你還好
But the sun will warm you soon.
陽光很快就會讓你暖和點的了
Sweetheart.You got to get moving.
寶貝，你需要站起來繼續前進
You got to come on down.
你一定要下回營地
My hands...
我的雙手···
frozen.
凍住了
My...
我···
My feet are frozen.
我的腳也凍住了
We're sending people up to you with tea and "O"s
我們正在送一些茶和氧氣上去給你
But, you got to get moving, Rob.
Can you hear me?
但，你也必須走起來，羅布
你聽到我說的嗎？
You got to get your circulation going.
你需要讓你的機體運動起來
Okay, my love.
我知道了，我的愛人
You do it.
Do it right now!
趕快
現在就動起來
I love you.
我愛你
Over and out.
結束通話
Come on, Rob.
好吧，羅布
We can't carry them.
我們找不到他的了
That's not possible.
沒可能做到
He's correct.
他是對的
It's going to take "O"
去找他也需要氧氣
just to get ourselves down.
就讓我們自己下去吧
Oh, damn it.
噢，該死的
Helen, it's Mike here.
Do you copy?
海倫，我是麥克
你聽到嗎？
Come in, Mike.
What do you got?
聽到了麥克
怎麼了？
Yasuko and Beck,
恭子和貝克
did not make it back to camp.
他們沒能回到營地
Okay, Mike.
Thanks for letting us know.
好吧，麥克
感謝你告知我們
[NOT RETURNED]
[SOUTH COL, CAMP 4]
[南側，4號營地]
Meg.
梅格
Bud.
柏格
Hello, Base Camp.
你好，大本營
Ang Dorjee, this is Helen.
昂多吉，我是海倫
We have to turn back!
我們需要回去
There is the very bad storm again.
冰雪暴又來了
- Your call, Ang Dorjee.
- Sorry.
- 你說吧，昂多吉。
- 抱歉
We'll try to do again, when the storm pass.
等冰雪暴過去了，我們會再次嘗試上去的。
We'll leave some tea and oxygen here.
我們把氧氣和熱茶留在這
Sorry.
抱歉
We have to tell Rob they're not coming.
我們必須告訴羅布他們沒有繼續前進
Okay.
好的
Hey, Rob.
It's Guy, mate.
嘿，羅布
我是蓋爾，夥計
Guy.
蓋爾
I can't stop shaking, Guy.
我在不停地發抖，蓋爾
The boys hit a bit of a high wind.
And...
兄弟們遇上了點強風
your best shot is going to be to get lower.
所以你最好盡可能地往下走
Let me think about it.
讓我想想
Don't think I can hang out here another night.
我想我應該無法在這埵A撐一個晚上的
We'll try again first thing, okay.
我們會盡量嘗試再上去的，好嗎？
Helen?
海倫？
Yeah.
是
Yeah, he's still there.
是的，他仍在堅持
He's just below the South Summit.
他就在山峰南側下面
He's got oxygen but...
他拿到氧氣，但是···
it's iced up.
氧氣被凍住了
We don't know whether he's been able to free it.
我不知道是否他能夠打開它
Is anybody with him?
還有人跟他一起嗎？
No.
沒有
You have to get him down before dark.
He won't survive another night.
如果不在入夜前把他救出來，他就沒辦法熬再熬過一個晚上了
We know.
我們知道
But the storms come back,real bad.
但風暴又來了，真的很糟糕。
We can't get anyone up to him tonight.
今晚我們沒有人能趕上去
We tried.
我們盡力了
He might as well be on the moon.
他可能熬不過今晚
Uh.
恩
Can you put me on with him again?
你能再幫我聯繫下他嗎？
Of course.
當然可以
Guy. Get Rob.
蓋爾 聯繫羅布
Hi, Rob.
It's Guy.
你好，羅布
我是蓋爾
I've got Jan for you.
我幫你聯繫到簡
Hold on.
等等
Give me a second.
等我會兒
Okay.
好的
Hi, sweetheart.
你好，寶貝
How are you?
你還好嗎？
I'm thinking about you.
我很想念你
Please say, "I'm good."
告訴我「你很好」好嗎？
Are you warm, my love.
你感到有些暖了沒，我的愛人
I might have a little frostbite.
我應該有些凍傷了
I'm looking forward to making it all better.
我正嘗試讓自己好點
Can't wait for you to come home.
我都快等不急你回家了
How's Sarah?
莎拉還好嗎？
Sarah?
莎拉？
Yeah.
是的
Yes, Sarah is good.
很好，莎拉這個名字挺好的
Will you call her that for me?
你會為了我用這個名字嗎？
Yes, I will.
會的，我會的
I don't think I'm going to get to meet her.
我覺得我應該見不到她了
I'm so sorry.
很對不起
Don't say that.
別這樣說
If anyone can make it, you can.
其他人也許不行，但你一定可以的
Remember.
記住
I love you.
我愛你
Please don't worry too much.
請你別太擔心我
Good bye, my love.
再見，我的愛人
I love you, Rob.
我愛你，羅布
I love you.
我愛你
(Come on.)
（加油·）
(Come on, Dad.)
（加油，爸爸）
Beck.
貝克
Helen, it's Mike here.
海倫，我是麥克
Helen, do you copy?
海倫，你聽到嗎？
Mike, come in.
麥克，我聽到
Beck's still alive.
貝克仍然生還
He walked himself into camp.
他自己一個人走回了營地
I got to get him down to Camp 1.
我需要把他送到1號營地
Thanks, Mike.
謝謝，麥克
We don't even know how,but he is alive.
我們也不知道他如何做到的，但他活下來了
The thing is, Peach,
事實是，桃子
we can't get him down the Icefall.
我們無法把他送到冰柱那邊
Oh no.
I'll get him down.
我會把他送下來的
- I'll get him down. Okay.
- Dad.
- 我會把他送下來的，好嗎
- 爸爸
Okay, what do we need?
We need a helicopter, right?
好的，我們需要些什麼？
我們需要直升機，是嗎？
Yeah, but they can't a helicopter up
that high because the air is too thin.
是的，但直升機無法上來這
因為這堛漯躓薴茧}薄了
We should try, but it is one heck of a rescue.
我們應該試一下，但這次救援真的很麻煩
And he's not in a good way, Peach.  So...
並且他的狀況也不太好，桃子。所以
I don't want you to get your hopes up too high.
我希望你不要抱有太高的期望
1 step at a time.
一步一步來
- You got to keep moving.
- I'm tired.
- 你需要繼續
- 我盡力了
- I know.
- I'm tired.
- 我知道
- 我在盡力了
I know you are.
I know you are. Come on.
我知道你在盡力
我知道你在盡力，加油。
Slow and steady.
慢慢來，保持穩定。
Come on, keep moving.
加油，堅持住。
Yes, I like the number of the American Embassy in Kathmandu, Nepal.
是的，我想知道在尼泊爾加德滿都的美國大使館的電話。
Yes, Nepal.
是的，尼泊爾
Ambassador, please.
No. Sweets, I can't hold.
大使，請
不，大使，我不能等
No. You listen, sir.
不，先生你聽著
My husband has already died once as you've seen on the news.
我的丈夫就像你看到的新聞一樣就快不行了
Trust me. Having him die a second time is not going to play well on CNN.
相信我，如果他的死被CNN報道出來了將不會是什麼好事
There we go, buddy.
來吧，夥計
That's it, alright.
就是這樣，好的
CAMP TWO
2號營地
- Beck.
- Uh-huh.
- 貝克
- 恩-恩
How're you doing?
還好嗎？
Oh, you know,
third amendment.
噢，你懂的，好很多了
Warming up?
暖些了嗎？
I'm not sure yet.
我還不太確定。
Look like you are,a little bit.
看上去還是好點的
How's Rob doing?
羅布怎樣了？
Rob's still up there right now.
羅布現在還在上面
And Doug,what's he up to?
那道格拉斯，他怎樣了？
Doug's gone, Beck.
道格拉斯去世了，貝克
I don't know. No one's ever try to fly higher than Base Camp before.
我不知道。沒有人嘗試過飛過大本營上空
They gonna give it a go.
他們需要放手一搏
And find an LZ. Just mark up with whatever you can.
並且要找到降落點，盡可能標誌出你們的位置
Okay.
Worth a try.
好的
值得一試
Thanks, Guy.
好的，蓋爾
Grab a Gatorade.
Got a chopper coming in.
拿幾瓶佳得樂
等下會有直升飛機過來
We need to make a LZ
我們需要做個降落點
We got a chopper coming in!
等下有直升飛機過來！
- Clear the rope back to the tents!
- Okay.
- 把繩子清回到帳篷堶
- 好的
Thanks.
好的
Keep it clear.
Keep this whole area clear.
保持空曠
保持這片區域空曠
Come on.
來吧
We're doing fine.
我們可以的
It's not possible.
沒可能做到的
You land here,we'll never get back up.
要是在這媯蛦高爾隉A我們就永遠飛不回去了。
Okay, Major, let's go back.
好的，少校，讓我們回去吧
- That's it.
- Can't get any more out.
- 只能這樣了
- 帶不了都少東西了
it's as light as we're going to get it.
現在應該夠輕了
- Tango to Charlie.
- 探戈呼叫查理
Right here!
這堙I
Come on!
Let's go! Let's go!
來吧！
出發吧！出發吧！
Come on, Beck.
來吧，貝克
Nearly there.
就快到了
Okay.
Come on.
好的
來吧
1 person.
1個人
- Only 1 person.
- Just him, just 1.
- 只能帶一個人
- 就他，只能一個人
- Alright.
- There you go.
- 好了
- 起飛吧
You good?
你還好嗎？
I'm going to lift the tail up.
Fly us over the edge.
我現在要起飛離開這埵^到山下
- Is that okay with you?
- I'm with you.
- 沒問題吧？
- 沒問題
Good, man.
好的，兄弟
Get yourself inside, go on.
快進入堶悼h，來吧
It's alright, Anatoli.
好的，阿納托利
I'm so sorry, Helen.
非常抱歉，海倫
Come on.
Let's get you inside.
沒事
讓我扶你進去。
Hi, Peachy.
你好，桃子
Beck.
貝克
Thank you so much, darling.
謝謝你，寶貝
Oh, Jan.
I'm so sorry.
噢，簡
非常抱歉
羅布的遺體仍然在和其他遇難者一樣留在山上
斯科特·菲捨爾
安迪'哈羅德·哈里斯
道格·漢森
Yasuko Namba
恭子南玻
探險顧問團隊 1966年
貝克韋瑟斯失去了雙手和鼻子
他仍舊和他的妻子桃子在達拉斯居住
1996年7月，簡生下了一個女嬰。
她的名字叫莎拉
莎拉·阿諾德-賀